<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The citizen's companion: or The trades-man's mirrour Wherein most parts of a trading life are accomodated to the judgments and examples of the ancients. A work enrich'd with proverbs, and historically beautified with the deeds and sayings of the wisest and worthiest men that ever were in the world.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4338</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216321</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828053</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828053</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32480</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33182)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32480)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2975:5, 1944:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The citizen's companion: or The trades-man's mirrour Wherein most parts of a trading life are accomodated to the judgments and examples of the ancients. A work enrich'd with proverbs, and historically beautified with the deeds and sayings of the wisest and worthiest men that ever were in the world.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 157, [1] p., plate   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for Barber Tooth, near York-House in the Strand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With additional engraved title page, not filmed.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Bodleian Library (reel 1944:18) and Folger Shakespeare Library (reel 2975:5).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32480:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CITIZENS COMPANION: OR THE TRADES-MAN'S MIRROUR.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN Moſt parts of a Trading Life are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated to the Judgments and Examples of the ANCIENTS.</p>
            <p>A WORK Enrich'd with Proverbs, and Hiſtorically beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with the Deeds and Sayings of the Wiſeſt and Worthieſt Men that ever were in the World.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Otium Ingenii rubigo.</l>
               <l>Juſtitia ſine Prudentia plurimum poterit,</l>
               <l>Sine Juſtitia nihil valebit Prudentia.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>Barber Tooth,</hi> near <hi>York-Houſe</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:32480:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32480:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER, Of what Quality or Calling ſoever.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is as common to ſee a <hi>Preface</hi> (which is the key ordinarily to unlock the deſign of every good and ſolid Author) ſtand begging the favour of its <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> to every idle <hi>Tract,</hi> and therein to imitate the method, more than to deſerve the reward of the beſt Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; as to behold <hi>Fantaſtical,</hi> and <hi>inſipid Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> to deck their <hi>out-ſides;</hi> nay, (in ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) to out-ſtrip rather than keep pace in <hi>Faſhions</hi> with <hi>Gentlemen.</hi> Yet the <hi>Compiler</hi> of the following matter is not ſo Cynical or crazy in his judgment, as to deem handſom apparel un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy or unbecoming a <hi>Citizen;</hi> but it's the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancy, ſingularity,</hi> and <hi>gay preciſeneſs</hi> of too
<pb facs="tcp:32480:3"/>many now adays, that urges him to a compariſon of this nature. For certainly the <hi>value</hi> of the greateſt part of the <hi>ſpruceſt</hi> and moſt <hi>modiſh</hi> that a Shop contains, are as ſubject to the cenſure of Pens far more biting and reprehenſive, than mine; as <hi>Prefaces</hi> of the aforeſaid kinde, are to the merit of being made Bum-fodder, and onely to ſet up Candles. However, the chiefeſt, at leaſt the moſt in number of my <hi>Peruſers,</hi> will be apt to ask (as indeed they have ſome reaſon, an Author's name ſwaying ſo much oftentimes in the Sale of a Book) <hi>pray who is this, that profeſſes ſuch verbal kindneſs, and as if he ſpoke through a Vizor, or was afraid of thanks, ſeems to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us inviſibly?</hi> Truly, <hi>ingratitude,</hi> and the <hi>fineneſs</hi> (amongſt the reſt of mankind) <hi>of moſt of our</hi> Cit's Ears <hi>and</hi> Eyes, and conſequently of their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings, obliges him to conceal himſelf to a <hi>Publick</hi> knowledge. <hi>Ingratitude</hi> on one ſide is managed by <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Envy,</hi> ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantageouſly to the fame and deſerts of any that endeavour to ſtop the violent courſe of <hi>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> eſpecially as it runs and rages at preſent too frequently amongſt <hi>Traders,</hi> that <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Ignorance</hi> ſhall move them ſooner to revil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their <hi>juſt Rebukers</hi> (who have the comfort of being warranted in ſuch ſufferings by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of our Saviour, and a world of others mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in Sacred and Prophane Hiſtory, for their
<pb facs="tcp:32480:3"/>Piety, Wiſdom, and meekneſs) than to repay them with that love, kindneſs, and common reſpect <hi>meer Society,</hi> and <hi>civil community</hi> lays a claim to; if they were not <hi>bound</hi> (as undeniably they are) to wiſh well, honour, and procure the benefit of <hi>thoſe,</hi> who hazard their <hi>temporal felicity</hi> to ſave them Body and Soul. They who concur not with me in opinion (wherein they may be eaſily enlightned) chiefly as to <hi>morality,</hi> exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyfied in thoſe inſertions which Hiſtory hath afforded for the ſtrengthening what I argue on; though I think I have fortified my endeavours too impregnably in all particulars, with the <hi>acts</hi> and <hi>judgments</hi> of the <hi>wiſeſt men,</hi> but above all of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> himſelf: yet to touch you my Viewer (and it may be pert Cenſurer) hereof more to the quick, let me tell you that I have changed my former reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of ſending my <hi>Companion</hi> abroad without a <hi>Preface;</hi> and becauſe I would not obſcure my ſelf for want of one, and be <hi>Proverbially</hi> judged <hi>out of the World,</hi> being <hi>out of the Mode,</hi> ſuch a <hi>one</hi> as it is, take it; but obſerve heedfully (or you will one day ſmart for it) thoſe <hi>Precepts</hi> which I have choſen from <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Armory, as well to guard my ſelf from any ones captiouſneſs, as to overthrow all obſtacles raiſed by partiality, miſ-conceit, or that pleaſure every one too unreaſonably purſues in worldly enjoyments. But my own defenſe being contain'd only in the <hi>Preface,</hi> behold how
<pb facs="tcp:32480:4"/>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> or <hi>Wiſdomes Self</hi> denounces, <hi>That re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs of inſtruction are the way of life;</hi> and that <hi>he that heareth them, abideth among the wiſe;</hi> but <hi>he that hateth them is bruitiſh, and ſhall dye,</hi> Prov. <hi>6.23.15, 31.12, 1.</hi> They who are leſs tainted, and ſo have the leſs need of a Phyſician, will undoubtedly manifeſt themſelves to <hi>underſtand knowledge,</hi> to be no <hi>Scorners,</hi> but to <hi>favour their rebuker, beyond a flatterer,</hi> Prov. <hi>19.25.9, 8.28, 28.</hi> Whether my Reader doth me Juſtice, or no, yet I have this invincible refuge, <hi>To them that reprove the wicked ſhall be delight, and a good bleſſing ſhall come upon them,</hi> Prov. <hi>24.25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In my next place, for <hi>Citizens niceneſs,</hi> (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that of whole Mankind) it is too cuſtomary to diſlike, what they hear or read, if not delivered in a <hi>quaint, pithy,</hi> and <hi>alluring ſtile,</hi> more towards tickling their ſenſes, than improving their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings; far be it from my <hi>Citizen</hi> to hug him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in ſuch conceits, and <hi>with this fooliſhneſs to pervert his way,</hi> Prov. <hi>19.3.</hi> Now to imagine upon viewing the <hi>Title,</hi> that becauſe it talks of <hi>Antients Deeds</hi> and <hi>Sayings,</hi> of neceſſity ſuch trumpetting at the dore, can't chooſe but declare ſome rare ſight within, worth your time and Money: Indeed (who e'r you be,) you will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur a great miſtake to expect much <hi>Art</hi> in a <hi>Piece</hi> intended for <hi>Vulgar uſe,</hi> which would have fitted
<pb facs="tcp:32480:4"/>it rather for <hi>Scholars</hi> than <hi>Shop-keepers,</hi> and would have wrought the ſame effect in <hi>Trade,</hi> as <hi>Prayers</hi> in Latine do in the <hi>Romiſh Religion.</hi> For whereas the <hi>education</hi> of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined by <hi>ignorance,</hi> in reference to all things hidden in Learning, it would have proved very impracticable, (had any attempted it) to have expoſed, for the practice of the meaneſt degrees of people, what ſhould be hard to apprehend without a <hi>Dictionary.</hi> Beſides, albeit my remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>in cognito</hi> to the moſt, may inſtigate ſome, (for their own readier excuſe) to think hard, and judge the Author, (like a Beadle with his dark Lanthorn, who ſees all things ſave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, walks the Rounds to ſcare Rakehels, yet ſometimes participates of the ſweet of their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, becauſe the poor man is frail) to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with more light of Nature than Grace, and to mix erroneouſly his own actions with fleſh and blood. It's confeſs'd, I am none of thoſe, <hi>Who can ſay I have made my heart clean, I am free from my ſin,</hi> Prov. <hi>20.9.</hi> Nevertheleſs (I thank God for it) ſince I began to underſtand the World, and to deal properly with men, I have as few in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances both on my reputation and eſtate, as any of my ſtanding. I ſhan't inſiſt too long on my own vindication, leſt I render my ſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to the imputation of <hi>flying</hi> (through guilt) <hi>when none purſueth.</hi> For what I aſſert in the
<pb facs="tcp:32480:5"/>ſhaping of my <hi>Pattern</hi> for a <hi>Trading life,</hi> the Teſtimonies are ſo evident, and the exigence of the Age ſo pinching and exacting, as I ſhould have dipt my hand in the ruine of not a few, had I deferred any longer thoſe <hi>inſtructive</hi> and <hi>repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive remedies,</hi> which are ſo wanted, ſo little minded or promoted by any whoſe <hi>abler parts, better leiſure,</hi> and <hi>apter utenſils,</hi> would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed mightily to the <hi>reformation</hi> of <hi>Citizens manners,</hi> and to the cleanſing them from thoſe corruptions <hi>ill courſes</hi> have filled them with; to the diſparagement of Commerce, to a forced diſtruſt of one another, but finally and eſpecially for committing thoſe tranſgreſſions which retard the conqueſt of our Enemies, whoſe down fall, with our own amendment, (which is the only way for obtaining it) will compleat the luſtre of our <hi>City,</hi> which will be celebrated, and <hi>rejoyce when it goeth well with</hi> thoſe ſhall deſerve the name of <hi>Righteous,</hi> Prov. <hi>11.10.</hi> I never intended to court any ones candour; but the <hi>Preſs,</hi> (as it ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is otherwiſe) hath here and there made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> few ſcapes; wherefore to blame me, would be <hi>through ſudden anger to deal fooliſhly;</hi> but (on all occaſions) <hi>it will be your glory to pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> over a tranſgreſſion,</hi> Prov. <hi>14, 17.19, 11.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32480:5"/>
            <head>THE <hi>CITIZEN'S COMPANION:</hi> OR THE <hi>Tradeſ-man's Mirrour,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IT might be expected from me, to ſpeak ſomething in the Praiſe of a <hi>Trade</hi> or <hi>Calling;</hi> But the benefit accruing by it both to <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>particulars,</hi> is too perſpicuous; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ational, uſeful and honourable to need <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny Apology. 'Tis true, that for the ſeven, eight, or nine years of Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhip undergone by a Servant, ſome have been ſo frighted at a <hi>Civil ſubjection</hi> for ſo long a term, as rather to miſpend and caſt away the apteſt part of their dayes in <hi>Idleneſs (the Mother of all miſchief)</hi> or, any how, (having the face of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile (though moſtly in the end a perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious) liberty) than to ſubmit to the commands of a <hi>Shop-keeper,</hi> or to reject
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32480:6"/>that airy enjoyment which is aim'd at by Youth; and (becauſe moſt concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with corrupt Nature) is embraced before any thing not ſo eaſie in the attainment. It would grow a <hi>mad world</hi> if Children ſhould be allowed to be their own chooſers: <hi>A Child left to himſelf bringeth his Mother to ſhame,</hi> Prov. 9.15. certainly if raw and ignorant judgments were determinable in a buſineſs of that Nature, their poor and inſipid inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions would pitch as ſoon on the worſe courſes for the future maintenance of their bodies, as they are prone to prefer <hi>playing the Truant</hi> to going to School, and thereby loſing thoſe opportunities, ſo expedient for the beautifying of their minds. <hi>Fooliſhneſs is bound in the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of a Child</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) but the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of correction ſhall drive it far from him</hi> Prov. 22.15. <hi>Parents</hi> muſt then a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cuſtome their Sons to a ſtricter libert than commonly they enjoy. They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> more indulgent than diſcreet, if for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> little crying they ſhall remit and ſlacke that obedience they naturally and legall have over their Children, eſpecia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knowing by their own ſometimes wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> experience, the ill conſequence of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32480:6"/>cuſtoms, and the miſery attending inconſideration. <hi>Withold not correction from thy child, for if thou beateſt him with a rod he ſhall not dye,</hi> Prov. 23.13. How many depending on the fruits of a petty patrimony, have begged or ſtole before they dyed! Therefore every Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought to uſe his Authority in plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Sons judiciouſly to their future benefit, not omitting the ſuiting of each ones inclination to a <hi>Trade</hi> moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. My <hi>Citizen,</hi> by ſuch a means falling under the remarks and advice of this Diſcourſe, if he daigns to make it his <hi>Companion</hi> till he hath read it over, he may become of my opinion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it a <hi>happy thing</hi> for a man to go through his affairs without <hi>Injuſtice;</hi> which he cannot do, ſave by being Maſter of his affections and appetites, and by a narrow inſpection into all his Actions; that maturely conſulting and diſcreetly managing his buſineſs, he may live <hi>juſtly</hi> with <hi>pleaſure</hi> and <hi>profit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hot <hi>Youth</hi> running inconſiderately, and giving time no leaſure to do any thing for him, ſpeeds <hi>unjuſtly</hi> and with trouble; but catches nothing, at leaſt <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing durable.</hi> And a dull-ſpirited man,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32480:7"/>not taking occaſion when 'tis ready<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miſſeth his advancement, yet is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> freed from cares and perplexity; both theſe truſting to <hi>Fortune</hi> the Goddeſs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Raſhneſs</hi> and <hi>Sloth,</hi> their unskilfullne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> effects their deſtiny. The
<note n="a" place="margin">Jullice.</note> 
               <hi>firſt</hi> coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the three is beſt, the
<note n="b" place="margin">Raſhneſs.</note> 
               <hi>ſecond</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Stupidity.</note> 
               <hi>third may</hi> riſe, but it is very doubtful the firſt <hi>muſt</hi> of neceſſity be promoted the order of his actions being ſet down in <hi>His</hi> Decree that made him. Thus it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in all Profeſſions; no <hi>Tradeſman</hi> can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> counted good, except he be a <hi>real</hi> good man; opening his Conſcience, living<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if he were alwayes in publick, rather fearing himſelf than others; by this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> raiſeth himſelf above and beyond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fear, contemning the blows of <hi>Fortu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> His <hi>wiſdom</hi> without this will be e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, his <hi>policy</hi> will be <hi>knavery;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>honeſty</hi> without <hi>wiſdom</hi> is unprofitable <hi>Wiſdom</hi> (ſaith a Learned man) <hi>of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> gifts of God is moſt pure; ſhe inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goodneſs into her Diſciples, ſhe pardo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the wicked, ſhe maketh the poor ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and the rich honourable, and ſuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> feignedly embrace her, ſhe makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> like to God. <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is the beau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and noble compoſition of him, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:32480:7"/>Word, Actions, and Motions; could the eyes ſee <hi>her,</hi> ſhe would ſtir up wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful love; by <hi>her</hi> he enfranchiſes his Spirit, from an <hi>unjuſt</hi> ſubjection unto unneceſſary things, and out of his <hi>calling. Socrates</hi> (according to the judgement of Phyſiognomers) naturally given to all wickedneſs, by the ſtudy of <hi>wiſdom</hi> reformed his lewd inclinations. And though <hi>Cicero</hi> in his latter dayes cryed out, <hi>Would I had never known what wiſdom meant;</hi> Yet <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> onely by his <hi>wiſdom</hi> and experience brought all his deſigns to effects. However, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>little</hi> knowledge to be unfruitful; yet the courſe of a general Learning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too long, the purchaſed experience muſt be pertinent and within the pale of his own <hi>calling,</hi> and is to be proſecuted diligently, becauſe none is ſo eaſie to be dived into (as it were) in a moment. A courſe may be ſoon begun, but every one is ſure of meeting with unforeſeen rubs. As no humane action is delivered to the World without many circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; ſo there is no <hi>Trade</hi> without them: there is no circumſtance in it but is a ſtep mounting the underſtanding to the true value and clear perſpection of it. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32480:8"/>it would be eſteemed a great piece of ſottiſhneſs to enſlave ones ſelf, and to be ſo over-exact and induſtrious, as like <hi>Nicias</hi> the Painter, (who was ſo earneſt and intentive in his profeſſion) t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forget food, and omit the reception o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nature's ſupport. And <hi>Apelles</hi> the Pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter uſed to chide <hi>Protagines;</hi> who no knowing when a thing was well, would never keep his hands from the Table<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If it could be attain'd, the diſcretion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>CRISP<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> is to be imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated, who under a colour of negligen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accompliſhed whatever he undertoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Though curioſity and excellency are the leſs reprehenſive, becauſe ſetting fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the glory of a mans Countrey; ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mean and moderate care is to be concl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ded on, becauſe the <hi>Bow too long bent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſubject to breaking.</hi> If an extream <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be admitted, it ought to tend to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ready curing of our <hi>exceſſes</hi> and vic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appetites. Nor are they ſo hard to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conquered, if we will but a little t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the paths of our <hi>Anceſtors. Julius C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was of a conſtitution infirm and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vulſive, yet he ſcorned to ſubmit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> feeble and ſlothful inclination; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſought a remedy in War, fighting ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:32480:8"/>his Diſtemper, with continual labour and exerciſe, lying for the moſt part in the open air. <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> was ſuch an enemy to pleaſure, as in the moſt Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val times to cauſe his head to be ſhaven, hindring thereby his forwardneſs to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in publick, and ſticking the cloſer to his Studies. Certainly <hi>diligence</hi> in all points is a thing of that moment, as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great and noble action ows unto it the means of atchievement. <hi>Cleanthes</hi> in the night-time carried water, and in the day he hearkned attentively to the Philoſophical Lectures read by <hi>Chryſippus.</hi> The <hi>Romans</hi> allowed every hour of the day to ſome exerciſe or other. <hi>Alexander</hi> never ſlept ſave with his arm ſtretcht out of the bed, holding in his hand a Silver Ball, having a Silver Baſon by his Bed-ſide, that leſt he ſlept too ſecurely and ſoundly, the falling of the Ball might awake him, and admoniſh him of his Enemies. Examples are numberleſs if I would crowd them in ſo little room. But remitting ſuch kind of incitations, and <hi>Youthful</hi> inſtigations to <hi>Vertue,</hi> to their patter places, and more proper inſertions; I ſhall now begin to define my <hi>Citizen,</hi> as one who hath ſerved ſeven years, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32480:9"/>is entring on the Worlds Stage, to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to all dealers with him, that no advantage or lucre can ſhake his ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded <hi>juſtice,</hi> (rather like <hi>Ariſtides</hi> the <hi>Athenian,</hi> to leave behind him not enough to bury him, than wrong any man, and loſe after his death the Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name of <hi>Juſt</hi>) declaring by his ſmooth deportment to all, that he imitates the wiſe Lord <hi>Burleigh,</hi> in putting off his Cares with his Cloaths; and by the improvement of his <hi>Fortunes</hi> and <hi>Stock,</hi> raiſing himſelf (by a bleſſing on his inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vors) to the higheſt Dignity <hi>reputation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wealth</hi> can advance him; uſing <hi>Demoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> his diligence, who was grieved to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e any one up before him, which made hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in his Profeſſion as an <hi>Oratour</hi> to pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the moſt famous of his Time.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:32480:9"/>
               <head>Of Juſtice.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſtice</hi> by the Poets is fained to be a a <hi>Virgin,</hi> and to have raigned among men in the <hi>golden world;</hi> but being by them abus'd, forſook the world and returned to Heaven. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> makes mention of a certain <hi>Jeſter</hi> who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to tell all the people what they moſt deſired; ſtanding up, he ſaid with a loud voice, <hi>You would buy cheap, and ſell dear.</hi> To do ſo as it was in his time, ſo it is in ours common; but a Common vice, unleſs it be limited. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, if ever <hi>buying</hi> and <hi>ſelling</hi> was corrupted, it was but venial and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in compariſon to that of our times. If <hi>Thievery</hi> may claim the epithite of <hi>lawful,</hi> and if authority in bargaining may not be abus'd, then the wicked Cuſtomes of ſome men may uncontroul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably be eſtabliſhed for Laws. But I am ſure they therein follow their own <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate allowances,</hi> not caring, ſo it be a <hi>Pennyworth,</hi> how and by whom it is conveyed to their hands. It is uſual
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32480:10"/>(would to God it were leſs Epidemical and Sinful) for <hi>Tradeſmen,</hi> chiefly <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailers</hi> of ſecond-hand Commodities, to faſten inconſiderately on all <hi>proffered goods,</hi> ſeldom minding the perſon and the power of the <hi>Seller.</hi> What unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and raſh dealing is this? How can any one pretend to the Priviledges o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Society, to the marks of <hi>loving his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as himſelf,</hi> to fulfil the Commands layd upon him by an <hi>All-ſeeing Eye,</hi> when to purchaſe more than ordinary advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, he ſhall knaviſhly (at leaſt impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citly) connive at <hi>theft,</hi> to the debaſing of Divine and Humane Laws, to the extream dammage of Maſters or Father<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but chiefly in hardning of ſuch parties as pick a ſecure ſweetneſs out of filching who get by degrees ſuch a habit, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many for lack of timely correction, ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> continued thoſe courſes, till it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> too late to take up, and have ſiniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their unfortunate lives by an infam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> death, to the ſorrow and great grief <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Parents and Maſters, (that have any kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for their Servants) and laſtly to the <hi>Buyers</hi> diſparagement, if not puniſhment at leaſt, thereby lying liable to the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſticking curſes of thoſe afflicte
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32480:10"/>Souls, who if it had not been for them might have ſurvived honourably. That my <hi>Citizen</hi> may eſchew all <hi>blame, ſhame,</hi> and <hi>danger,</hi> ſubject to ſuch unworthy, baſe, and abominable courſes; Let him never <hi>buy</hi> any thing proffer'd at his Shop, without firſt inquiring into the diſpoſers power; eſpecially if he ſeem to be a School-boy, Apprentice, or Shirk, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ought to regard: next, he muſt take an account of the perſons Friends, Maſter, Habitation, and what elſe may contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to diſcovery. Then if what's offred be ſuſpected, as alwayes it is when ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by meer Boys, he muſt detain it till he be better inform'd how it was come by: but if through lazineſs or worſe intents he defers notifying it to the Perſons intereſs'd, his honeſty is but painted and formal, and his fault is treble to what it ſhould have been. Firſt, he furthers the loſs of the party before wronged, in not giving him warning for the future. Secondly, he occaſions the Pilferers continuance in his illegal wayes, it may be to his ſudden deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction both of Body and Soul. Thirdly, and laſtly, inſtead of righting his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, he robs him, being worſe than a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32480:11"/>Receiver (who is equal with the <hi>Thief,</hi>) becauſe under the Cloak of <hi>Juſtice</hi> he deceives both. Finally, if the pretended lawful diſpoſer look ſuſpitiouſly, and anſwer not pertinently to the queſtions put to him; my <hi>Citizen</hi> is bound to ſtop the Party, at leaſt the Goods, and to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them reſtored to the true Owners. <hi>If</hi> my <hi>Citizen</hi> eſteem a jot what is told him; if <hi>Reaſon, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> have any ſhare in him, he will abhor ſuch a ſcandalous and odious practice as I have inſiſted on; and by ſuch a <hi>hate</hi> he will purchaſe a peace of Conſcience, a laſting, eminent, and good fame, thereb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> avoiding <hi>Solomou</hi>'s cenſure, <hi>Whoſe is Partner with a Thief hateth his own Soul</hi> Prov. 29.24. And he will entitle him ſelf to that <hi>Little which is better wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> righteouſneſs, than great Revenues with out right,</hi> Prov. 16.8. That <hi>Juſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> may be kept in <hi>prizing</hi> Commoditie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the vulgar eſtimation of wiſe good m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is to be followed. Upon ſome the <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> hath pitched a <hi>price,</hi> which may be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miniſhed, not enhauns'd; becauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>price</hi> was ſet in favour of the buyer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all which, with the innumerable ſorts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> commodities, it is impoſſible for <hi>Law</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:32480:11"/>determine the value. Yet the <hi>Civil Law</hi> ſaith, that's the juſt price of a thing, <hi>if it be ſold for ſo much as it can,</hi> that is, ſaith <hi>Ameſius, for how much it can commonly be ſold,</hi> the affection of this or that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular man not conſidered: But where taxation or common eſtimation cannot, there <hi>without deceit,</hi> the judgment of the Owner muſt ſet the <hi>price.</hi> A <hi>Contract</hi> muſt be according to the equality of the thing, and that muſt be meaſured by the <hi>price</hi> given. For as Time is the meaſure of Buſineſs, ſo is <hi>price</hi> of Wares. If the <hi>price</hi> exceed the things worth, or <hi>that</hi> exceed the <hi>price,</hi> the <hi>equality</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi> is taken away: that both agree is the juſt rule of <hi>Trading;</hi> againſt which <hi>Deceit</hi> is oppoſite. <hi>The Soul of the wicked deſireth evil, his neighbour findeth no favour in his eyes,</hi> Prov. 21.10. To <hi>deceive,</hi> is to make ſhew of one thing, and bring in another, beſides the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Cuſtomer, by which more is given for Wares than they are worth; but it's ſeldome men ſell at an under-rate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> tells us, <hi>There is no greater plague for Juſtice, than for ſome men under the masks of honeſty to deceive others.</hi> His rule was exact that ſaid, <hi>A
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32480:12"/>wiſe man will not deceive, neither can he be deceived.</hi> So did his profeſſion of honeſty reſound, who choſe this Motto; <hi>To deceive or be deceived, is hateful to me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (and who not?) met with many that would <hi>deceive,</hi> but few that would be <hi>deceived.</hi> To cozen others is worſe than to be cozened, as a ſin is worſe than a croſs; not that every wile is a Sin. <hi>Lucius</hi> approaching the Boat wherein <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was,
<note place="margin">Euſebius.</note> ask'd for him, and was anſwered by him (who was known to <hi>Lucius</hi> only by name and not face) that <hi>Athanaſius was hard before him; if he made haſt he might overtake him:</hi> who being violent in his purſuit, miſs'd <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> This <hi>Arrian</hi> perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor was <hi>deceived</hi> by the truth ſpoken with wiſdom and a good conſcience; but that <hi>deceit</hi> which is the corruption of <hi>juſtice,</hi> I ſhall now ſpeak againſt; this ſtands more in the <hi>wills,</hi> than wits o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This is firſt againſt <hi>Nature:</hi> one Serpent doth not ſting another; and the Fiſhes of the Sea devour none but thoſe of contrary kinds. But the greateſt evil that befall man, come from man. <hi>Hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:32480:12"/>homini lupus,</hi> one man is a Wolf to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Lyons ſpared <hi>Daniel,</hi> the ravenous Birds ſed <hi>Eliah,</hi> but man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſeth cruelty upon man. <hi>As a mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who caſteth Firebrands, Arrows, and Death, ſo is the man that deceiveth his Neighbour,</hi> Prov. 26.18. Pope <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Sixth never did what he ſaid, his Son <hi>Borgia</hi> never ſaid what he meant to do,
<note place="margin">Guichar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din.</note> pleaſing themſelves in counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting and diſſimulation, but their ends were fatal, one being poyſoned, the other ſlain. <hi>Frederick</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, when the Senators were entring the Senate-houſe, would ſay to them, <hi>Caſt away two things, deceit and diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation.</hi> The crafty are like the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meleon,</hi> apt to all objects, capable of all colours; they cloak <hi>Hate</hi> with <hi>Holineſs, Ambition</hi> with good <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>Flattery</hi> with <hi>Eloquence;</hi> but whatever they pretend, the iſſue is diſhoneſt. <hi>An Hypocrite with his mouth deſtroyeth his Neighbour,</hi> Prov. 11.9. An old <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonian,</hi> who had coloured his hairs, diſcovered his head in a great Aſſembly, and made a Declaration of the matters he came about. <hi>Archidamus</hi> the King riſing up, ſaid, <hi>What truth can this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32480:13"/>ſpeak, whoſe heart is ſtained with ſpots of Hypocriſie and double dealing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, it is againſt civil Society, for the preſervation whereof it is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient that men converſe ſafely, without fear of being undermined by each other. Therefore one ſaid well, <hi>the firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Juſtice is not to hurt, the ſecond to endeavour to procure the common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, it's againſt <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> which teaches a man ſo much charity and patience, as to do well, and ſuffer ill. It was Propheſied that in the time of the Goſpel,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſucking child ſhould play upon the hole of the Aſp, and the weanel child ſhould put his hand upon the hole of the Cockatrice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, it is Theft. <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> the <hi>Athenian,</hi> ſpying a dead body richly adorned, paſſed by; but called to his Companion, <hi>Take up theſe, for thou a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not</hi> Themiſtocles: he could not ſtoop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> low as to gather gold out of blood and dirt; but he ſtoops lower that plucks it from the living, and commits a double theft, robbing <hi>himſelf</hi> of honour, and <hi>t'other</hi> of means and life. <hi>The way of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wicked is darkneſs, they know not at what they ſtumble,</hi> Prov. 4.19.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:32480:13"/>
               <p>Laſtly, it is odious to God. It is the will of God that no man oppreſs his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor defraud him;
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.6</note> for the <hi>Lord is the avenger of all ſuch. A good man obtaineth favour of the Lord; but a man of wicked devices ſhall be condemned,</hi> Prov. 12.2. And to <hi>good men,</hi> even to the Heathen, they counted no profit laſting which was got by fraud: (ſaith one amongſt them) <hi>I will overcome by Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Arts,</hi> (viz.) by <hi>Vertue, Labour,</hi> and <hi>Arms.</hi> In <hi>Athens</hi> it was a cuſtome, when men bought or ſold any thing, they came before the Magiſtrate appointed for the purpoſe, and there took an Oath that they had not dealt fraudulently, nor uſed any deceit. I have heard of a <hi>Turk</hi> that having bought ſome Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of an <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> wherein was inclos'd a great ſum of Money, unknown to both Parties; and finding it, made many Journeys in queſt of the <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> and at length meeting him, unaſk'd reſtor'd the Money. Are Heathens <hi>juſt,</hi> and thou <hi>unjust? What doth it profit thee to be call'd what thou art not?</hi> It is ſaid of the Jeſuites, They have retained nothing of Jeſus, but the name; and of the Popes, Who was call'd <hi>Bonifacius,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:32480:14"/>or <hi>Benefactor,</hi> was a Malefactor; <hi>Pius</hi> or Godly, was wicked; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus</hi> or civil, was rude and ſavage; <hi>Innocentius</hi> or harmleſs, was hurtful and peſtiferous; and <hi>Clementius</hi> or meek, was cruel and unmerciful. <hi>He that juſtifieth the wicked, and he that condemns the juſt, even both are an abomination to the Lord,</hi> Prov. 17.15. I would it might not be ſaid of many <hi>Christians,</hi> that they are but ſo in name, having good words, not anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble works; ſuppoſing more of Gods <hi>hearing</hi> than his <hi>ſeeing.</hi> But many eat that here, which they cannot digeſt in <hi>Hell</hi> hereafter.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Dives</hi> was ſent into <hi>Hell</hi> for not giving his own, whither ſhall they be ſent, that take that which is anothers?</p>
               <p>The unjuſt ways of cunning which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> would have my <hi>Citizen</hi> to ſhun, are many; as <hi>Flattery, Diſſimulation, Lying</hi> &amp;c. of which in their order. There be ſome whom <hi>Gain</hi> will transform into a ſhapes; let the <hi>Cuſtomer</hi> look how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e will, they like a Looking-glaſs wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have ſomething in them like him. The Old <hi>Law</hi> would not allow the <hi>Swan</hi> is mans meat, his Feathers being white, is Body black. Neither are thoſe fit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:32480:14"/>deal with man, whoſe pretences being fair, have ſoul practices. Theſe are the <hi>Aves Gaviae</hi> of the times; which Birds when <hi>Alphonſus</hi> King of <hi>Sicily</hi> lanch'd from the Shore, flew about the Ship; and he cauſing Meat to be thrown them, they had no ſooner taken it, but they flew away. <hi>Thus it is with me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>my Flatterers having received of me what they expected, withdraw their obſequiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and return no more, unleſs they are a hungry after new benefits.</hi> Moſt Shop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers reſpect, even ſo, laſts no longer than the Cuſtomer uſes them to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream advantage. <hi>Divines</hi> ſay that <hi>Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi> divides a man from himſelf; he thinks himſelf otherwiſe than he is. <hi>A houſe divided can't ſtand;</hi> which ſome unjuſt ones conſidering, by <hi>Flattery</hi> part a mans judgment from his will, and ſo deceive him. Oyl poured upon the <hi>Graſs-hopper,</hi> kills it; <hi>Vineger</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vives it. Flattery kills thoſe whom ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere harſh treating doth heal. <hi>A flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering mouth worketh ruine,</hi> Prov. 26.28. So much danger hath Flattery begotten, as the Emperour <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> ſtruck one who praiſed him too much, ſaying <hi>he hit him. Antigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:32480:15"/>King of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> told a Poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> who call'd him a <hi>God</hi> (therein obſerving his ſoothing) <hi>that the Groom of his Stool knew 'twas no ſuch matter. Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> when his <hi>Paraſite</hi> perſwaded him to think himſelf a <hi>God,</hi> reply'd, he knew himſelf by two ſpecial things to be Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and not a God, <hi>namely, by ſleep an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> carnal motions.</hi> Heavier and ſadder were their following Dooms. King <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> baniſh'd all <hi>Flatterers</hi> from their Counts. At <hi>Athens</hi> they were put to death as the ruine and plagues of the Countries they dwelt in. The <hi>Athenians</hi> put <hi>Tymagor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to death, becauſe to inſinuate with <hi>Dari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> he ſaluted him after the <hi>Perſian</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Whereby it is viſible how obnor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ous <hi>Flattery</hi> hath ever been eſteemed and the hatred it hath always con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, and the puniſhment a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have met withal. But it is not alw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſo in <hi>Trade.</hi> Some Cuſtomers will gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dull and diſpleaſed, if they be not of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whetted by <hi>Flattery;</hi> down-right ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeeches diſcontent them. For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe, as the <hi>Apostle</hi> ſaid, <hi>Be angry b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſin not:</hi> So I ſay, <hi>Flatter but ſin not</hi> it be poſſible. Yet it is my opinion
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32480:15"/>that amiable looks and fair ſpeeches will go far enough, we need ſeek no <hi>by-ways.</hi> It is better (ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi>) to fall among a ſort of <hi>Ravens,</hi> than to happen into the company of <hi>Flatterers.</hi> For the <hi>Ravens</hi> never eat a man till he be dead; But <hi>Flatterers</hi> will not ſpare to devour him while he is alive. <hi>Flattery</hi> is the corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of truth; a thing as pernicious, as truth is excellent. <hi>Flattery</hi> is like a Golden-pill, which outwardly giveth pleaſure, but inwardly is full of bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Laſtly, among other things, a <hi>Flatterer</hi> is known by this, that he doth not onely imitate friendſhip, but go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Diſſimulation</hi> is an evil more <hi>tolerable</hi> in a Citizen. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Plato</hi> the Mellifluous Philoſopher ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes all, not to diſſemble with a friend, either for fear of diſpleaſing him, or for malice to deceive him. Yet I ſaid it was more <hi>tolerable,</hi> becauſe it is with him, as with one who hath married a wiſe, whom he muſt uſe well, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing affection to her, though he can't love her: and indeed <hi>Divines</hi> hold it in ſome caſes lawful, to pretend one thing, and intend another: as in the caſe of our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32480:16"/>
                  <hi>Saviours</hi> going to <hi>Emaus</hi> with the two Diſciples; He made as if he would go further, to ſtir up their deſire of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: whatever he pretended, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſtay with them that night. If a man pretends a long journey by being booted and ſpur'd, but intends to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn ſuddenly to ſee what thoſe whom he puts in truſt would do; if he had gone, is no ſin: whereas if he had ſaid <hi>he would go ſuch a journey,</hi> and went not, had been a lye. But woe to them that diſſemble to an ill end; theſe have the voice of <hi>Jacob,</hi> but the hands of <hi>Eſau;</hi> they are <hi>ſmooth</hi> in their words, <hi>rough</hi> in their actions. <hi>A feigned equity</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine) is a double iniquity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe diſſimulation is iniquity it ſelf</hi> Let him know alſo, that he ſins thrice, that counterfeits himſelf good, to whom he may do ill. Let him dread the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fell on a King of <hi>Poland,</hi> who (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> great Diſſembler) had always this with his mouth; <hi>If it be not true, I would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Rats might eat me:</hi> which came to paſs for he was aſſail'd by them in ſuch manne at a Banquet, that neither his Guard Fire or Water could defend him fin them. <hi>Worms</hi> eat up the tongue of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32480:16"/>Cozener <hi>Neſtorius. Abſalom</hi> that Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of Hypocriſie, who was within a <hi>Nero,</hi> without a <hi>Cato;</hi> he had a <hi>pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted tongue,</hi> but not a <hi>painted puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Behold him hanging on a Tree, as unworthy of Heaven or Earth: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him thruſt through with three Darts, as worthy of a treble death. <hi>He that hateth, diſſembleth with his lips.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 26.24</note> Theſe Diſſemblers, like the <hi>Polypus,</hi> can take all colours to <hi>deceive.</hi> But how cowardly a humour is this, and how ſervile? He that diſſembles, muſt ſtill have a fearful eye upon himſelf, leſt he be diſcovered: his <hi>myſtery</hi> is poor; for he is ere long found out, and then not credited: all he ſpeaks is <hi>Apocryphal.</hi> O how excellent a thing is freedome! there is no better life, than to live accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to a mans nature, reſolving always to dip the tongues Pen in the hearts Ink, ſpeaking but what he thinks; to do otherwiſe is impiety, and deſerves the puniſhment the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on one, who profeſſing a rigid life, uſed to wear hair-cloth lin'd with purple. Yet to utter all he thinks, is emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent folly. <hi>Clytus</hi> for ſpeaking too bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Alexander,</hi> was kill'd by him.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32480:17"/>
                  <hi>Silence</hi> is moſt ſafe; and <hi>Phocion</hi> is to be imitated above all, whoſe cloſeneſs was a freedome, in expreſſing in a few words his matter, and ſurpaſſing therein (as it is ſaid) <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> himſelf whoſe eloquence excell'd all others.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>A lying tongue</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) hateth thoſe that are afflicted by it,</hi> Prov. 26.28. <hi>Lying</hi> is a baſe vice, is a ſickneſs of the ſoul, which cannot be cured, but by ſhame and reaſon: It is a menſtruous and wicked evil, that fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily prophaneth and defileth the tongue of man, which is conſecrated of God, for the utterance of his praiſe. <hi>It is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> part of a ſlave</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bias</hi>) <hi>to lye: It is the property of a lyar</hi> (ſaith the ſame) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>put on the Countenance of an honeſt ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that ſo by his outward habit he m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the more ſubtilly deceive.</hi> And the Poet is offended at it highly:
<q>
                     <l>Dare to be true, nothing</l>
                     <l>Can need a <hi>Lye:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A fault that needs it most,</l>
                     <l>Grows two thereby.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lying</hi> is pernicious to humane Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, contrary to Nature, and worſe tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:32480:17"/>Theft; for ſilence is more ſociable than untrue ſpeech: it is the worſe, becauſe ſo various; if it had but one viſage, there were ſome remedy for it, a man might take the contrary to it for truth. That which is <hi>good</hi> is certain and finite (ſaith Philoſophy) there is but one way to hit the mark. <hi>Evil</hi> is infinite and uncertain; there are a thouſand ways to miſs it. It is reported of the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that they offered humane blood to their <hi>Gods;</hi> but none other than what was drawn from their <hi>tongues</hi> and <hi>ears,</hi> for an expiation of the ſin of <hi>lying,</hi> as well heard as pronounced. Even thoſe that uſe this vice moſt, conceive the baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it, counting that the extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt injury that can be verbally done to them, to reproach them with the <hi>lye.</hi> They are not aſham'd to <hi>lye,</hi> but to be call'd <hi>lyars.</hi> The Tongue is connexed by veins to the brain and heart, by which Nature teacheth us, that it is to be govern'd by the Intellect, whoſe ſeat is in the head, ſo that it may agree with the heart. A man <hi>deceived</hi> through errour, may utter this or that falſhood, thinking that true, which is no proper <hi>lye.</hi> To ſpeak falſly, thinking it true, is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32480:18"/>to lye materially; to ſpeak truth, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it falſe, is to <hi>lye</hi> formally; but he that ſpeaks falſe, knowing it falſe, <hi>lyeth</hi> in the matter and form, and therefore perfectly. Thus to <hi>lye</hi> to ſave our lives we may not, much leſs to ſave or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our Wealth. <hi>Buy the truth, and ſell it not,</hi> Prov. 23.23. Memorable is the Example of that Woman in St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome;</hi> ſhe knew how to <hi>die,</hi> but not to tell an <hi>untruth.</hi> In a ſtrait where Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney or <hi>Juſtice</hi> muſt be left, rather loſe Money than <hi>Juſtice, There is no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cicero) between a</hi> Lyar <hi>and a Forſwearer; for whomſoever I can make to tell a lye, I can eaſily perſwade to forſwear himſelf.</hi> The <hi>Egyptians</hi> made a Law that every Lyar ſhould be put to death. The <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> uſed to degrade <hi>Lyars</hi> of all honour, and to cut out their tongues. <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> cauſed a Souldier to be nayled to a poſt by the tongue, for lying The <hi>Cretans</hi> for lying became deſpiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the whole world. But <hi>Truth</hi> hath two Champions, Wiſdome and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy; ſhe ſhines brighteſt when foil'd looketh moſt beautiful in rags, is beſs defended with nakedneſs, ſmiles before
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32480:18"/>the Judge, and needs no Oratour. <hi>The lips of truth ſhall be eſtabliſhed,</hi> Prov. 12.19. <hi>Pharamond</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> was named <hi>Waramond;</hi> that is, <hi>Truth. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Aurelius</hi> the Emperour, was called <hi>moſt True,</hi> becauſe he was never found in a Lye, nor ever failed in truth. <hi>Pyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhus</hi> the King of <hi>Epyrus,</hi> however an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to the <hi>Romans,</hi> yet gave this praiſe unto <hi>Fabritius,</hi> that a man might aſſoon turn him from <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>honeſty,</hi> as the <hi>Sun</hi> out of his courſe. <hi>The get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of treaſures by a lying tongue, is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity toſſed to and fro of them that ſeek death,</hi> Prov. 21.6. <hi>Lying</hi> then muſt be baniſhed and abominated. But this rule muſt be obſerved; as we may not <hi>lye,</hi> ſo we need not ſpeak all the <hi>truth.</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> makes mention of one <hi>Firmus,</hi> who when he was aſkt to tell where his friend was, leſt he ſhould be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his enemies hands, ſaid he would not tell. <hi>I will</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>neither lye or betray him.</hi> This man (ſaith <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>) was <hi>Conſtant</hi> in name, but more <hi>Conſtant</hi> in minde. Nor muſt <hi>Pompey</hi> the great be forgotten, who choſe rather to endure the burning of a finger, than to diſcloſe the ſecrets of the Senate. But
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32480:19"/>
                  <hi>Papilius</hi> went beyond him, who cut out his own tongue, and flung it in the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants face, becauſe he would not betray his Aſſociates, who together had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt him.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Among theſe <hi>Polluters</hi> of the tongue, <hi>Swearing</hi> muſt be ſpoken of; when the reſt will not ſerve turn, 'tis common to add <hi>Oaths:</hi> and indeed, what ſin ſo hainous, which he that makes haſt to be rich is afraid or aſhamed to commit? <hi>He that maketh haſt to be rich ſhall not be innocent,</hi> Prov. 28.20. But what need I ſay any thing againſt this, more than the commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain; for the Lord will not hold hint guiltleſs which taketh his name in vain?</hi> This Law (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) ſhould be to all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> as a thouſand <hi>Sermons:</hi> He that layeth his faith in pawn, bindeth his ſafety, his honour, and his ſoul to the redeeming it. Faith gives no honour to an <hi>Oath;</hi> yet Oaths broken diſhonour Faith. <hi>To ſwear and forſwear</hi> (ſaith <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riander,</hi> one of the ſeven Sages) <hi>is a vice ſo hateful, that ſlaves themſelves judge it worthy puniſhment.</hi> Yet all <hi>Oaths</hi> are not unlawful: we may <hi>Swear: but let
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32480:19"/>the light go before us. Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God, and ſerve him, and ſwear by his name,</hi> Deut. 6.13. How horrid a thing is it to call God to bear witneſs to trifles and lyes? <hi>What is it to ſwear</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine) but to call God to witneſs? if this was conſidered, many would not, as they do, make Rhetorick of an Oath, taking delight in that which moves Gods diſpleaſure.</hi> To <hi>forſwear</hi> is a greater ſin than to <hi>ſwear;</hi> for the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth not ſay,
<note place="margin">Jam. 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>My Brethren do not</hi> forſwear, <hi>but do not ſwear.</hi> Wouldſt thou be far from <hi>Perjury, ſwear</hi> not: falſe <hi>ſwearing</hi> is deadly; true <hi>ſwearing</hi> is dangerous. Thoſe who have wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt <hi>Stones</hi> have been afraid to <hi>ſwear</hi> falſly by them; and doſt thou not fear that <hi>God</hi> who is everywhere preſent, who ſees all things <hi>generally</hi> without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>evidently</hi> without doubt, <hi>immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> without forgetfulneſs? Let me tell the <hi>ſwearer</hi> in anothers words, <hi>Though the puniſhment may be deferred, yet it ſhall be heavy.</hi> Beſides all other curſes this is one; he will certainly be falſe to man, who is not true to <hi>Gods</hi> honour. O matchleſs folly, that men ſhould through open Sluces, let their ſouls run out for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing!
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32480:20"/>Wiſe men think more than they ſpeak, and to <hi>ſwear</hi> is the leaſt part of their knowledge. <hi>A man ſhall eat good by the fruit of his mouth; but the ſoul of the tranſgreſſour ſhall eat violence.</hi> Prov. 13.2. <hi>By the bleſſing of the upright</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) the City is exalted; but 'tis overthrown by the mouth of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> Prov. 11.11. And if the daily miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes which befall thoſe who uſe too often to call on the name of a Deity, who in a moments time they are as apt to ſlight, are not powerful enough to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my Citizen from participating of ſo contemptible a cuſtom; if the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of <hi>holy Writ,</hi> and the advice of all the Wiſeſt men ever were, conduce nothing to aboliſhing in him ſo much ignorance and fooliſhneſs as an <hi>Oath</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; then let the dooms of ſome wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> valued not at what rate they ſwore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they counted an <hi>Oath</hi> to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> more vertue and validity in it than a je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> let their ſad &amp; frightful departures te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and ſcare my <hi>Citizen</hi> from venturi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to ſwim in a water ſo rough. We w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> begin with <hi>Andronicus Comnenus,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> having ſwore to protect the Sons of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>manuel</hi> Emperour of <hi>Conſtantinopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:32480:20"/>contrary to his ſo ſolemn faith plighted, ſlew them, uſurped the Empire; and to compleat his happineſs, was not long after <hi>depoſed, hung up by the feet,</hi> and <hi>hewed to pieces for his perjury. Chriſtien</hi> King of <hi>Denmark</hi> paid dearly for his faithleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: for conceiving no tye to be in an adjured promiſe, he was dethroned, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd, and lived miſerably the reſt of his life, for all that he was ſupported by many great Friends. <hi>Melius Suffetius</hi> a Romane was torn in pieces by four Horſes, for having broken his faith, and trampled on that reverence, he ought to have paid a <hi>Deity.</hi> To conclude, <hi>He</hi> (ſaith <hi>Sigiſmundus) that accuſtometh himſelf to ſwearing, ſhall never eſcape thoſe plagues every Oath heaps up; whoſe torture alſo ſhall continue eternally, unleſs through an early and an unfeigned peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence he make his peace with his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, I muſt not ſkip thoſe ſlippery ones who with unjuſt <hi>weights</hi> and <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi> can <hi>deceive,</hi> though the vigilancy of authority ties them to true ones. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers weights and divers meaſures both of them are an abomination to the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 20.10</note> Yet they not remembring that God ſees
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32480:21"/>they do, they pervert juſtice. I have read that <hi>Ferdinand</hi> Emperour of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> poſſeſt a great number of Watches, wherein he much delighted. It pleaſed him once to put this his variety of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gold upon a Table, as if he would expoſe it to ſale: going aſide, a ſtander by, driven by a deſire of ſtealing, or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, ſnapt one of them; which the Emperour eſpying aſlant, called him to him, and held him in various diſcourſe, till the Watch ſtriking diſcovered the Hour and his Theft. He that deceiveth with unjuſt <hi>weight</hi> or <hi>meaſure,</hi> may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply this: what he hath done hath a <hi>tongue</hi> to diſcover him; beſides, his <hi>conſcience</hi> betrays him; nor for all being his own judge, can he be abſolved. He hath one witneſs within, and another without. <hi>His own iniquities ſhall take the wicked him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and he ſhall be holden with the cords of his ſins,</hi> Prov. 5.22. By th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time he bluſhes, where I leave him wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſtitution to repent, or in time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuffer the following penalty. In 1475 <hi>Robert Baſſet</hi> a Salter being Maior he was very vigilant to puniſh thoſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uſed falſe Weights and Meaſures; f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which miſdemeanors, ſeveral Bake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:32480:21"/>were ſet in the Pillory, and others ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely handled.</p>
               <p>Now I diſcover ſome <hi>falſe lights;</hi> their end is to make the Wares ſeem better than they are, that the <hi>Seller</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive for them more than they are worth. But do they that uſe them, think <hi>light</hi> can look upon the wares, and not <hi>He</hi> that made that <hi>light?</hi> Or will they think to enjoy the perfect <hi>light</hi> hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which adulterate <hi>it</hi> here? There was a preſumptuous Carrier, that travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the night, was told of certain dangerous Pits in the way, that if he had no care of his Horſe, he might regard his own life. <hi>I ſhut my eyes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and all things everywhere are plain.</hi> Like this man are thoſe, who cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling but there is danger, yet fear it not; they know <hi>Gods</hi> omnipreſence, but reverence it not. It is to be lamented, that men have too <hi>dark Shops;</hi> but more, that they have too <hi>dark minds:</hi> let them remember, who it was, ſaid,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.9</note> 
                  <hi>There is nothing which ſhall not be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt.</hi> A ſhop may be too <hi>dark,</hi> and it may be too <hi>light;</hi> therefore it is, or ſhould be ſo ordered, for the benefit of <hi>Buyer</hi> and <hi>Seller,</hi> that <hi>light</hi> may be by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:32480:22"/>art neither obſcured, not let in to much. For <hi>a good man obtaineth fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Lord, but a man of wicke devices ſhall he condemn,</hi> Prov. 12.2.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, It is ordinary to pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon the Sellers want of money, or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Buyers want of Commodities. This<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>robbing the poor, becauſe he is poor, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> oppreſſing the afflicted in the gate,</hi> Prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 22.22. But this ſhould move pity, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cruelty. <hi>The Lyon</hi> (ſaith <hi>Pliny) ſpare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the proſtrate;</hi> and ſhall man be ſo unjuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as to do leſs? or if a man, far be it from my <hi>Citizen,</hi> who converſing with moſt Men, ſhould have moſt Humanity.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, It is likewiſe unjuſt, as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, to buy Wares for time, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to pay for them at the time appointed The <hi>Indians</hi> of <hi>Guinee,</hi> when they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe any thing, will deliver a bundle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sticks</hi> equal to the <hi>Months</hi> and <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> they appoint; keeping for themſelve a bundle of the ſame number: eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day or moneth they take away a <hi>Stick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſo when all are removed they are aſſur'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the times expiration. Thus careful are they in obſerving their time, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how negligent are we! It was well ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by Reverend Biſhop <hi>Jewel, 'Tis our mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32480:22"/>that we are called Chriſtians, yet live like Heathens under that name; nay, it were well, if we did as theſe Heathens.</hi> They which are ſo backward, are like ill Singers (ſaith one) they ſhould be ſent to the Compter, a good Singing-ſchool for them to learn to keep better time in.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, But what ſhall we think of thoſe which will finde no time at all to pay, <hi>breaking</hi> deeply indebted to many? I know what they will alledge in their defence; it was deſtined, <hi>Providence</hi> had decreed they ſhould not proſper. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to have read, that <hi>Zeno Citicus</hi> having a ſervant ſurpris'd in ſtealing, commanded him to be ſlain; who plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for himſelf, ſaid <hi>the Fates had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed him to ſteal. And to ſuffer too,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed <hi>Zeno.</hi> So for thoſe that <hi>break,</hi> eſpecially out of Policy to deceive, let them prove its decree, the puniſhment is ſure enough. Was there ever any of theſe, but it might be ſaid of him, <hi>He felt the ſmart of it?</hi> He may ſeem to proſper for a time, and we may won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the <hi>way of the wicked</hi> ſhould do ſo; but Divinity it ſelf will anſwer us, Iſa. 48.22. <hi>There is no peace to the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:32480:23"/>wicked:</hi> if no <hi>Peace,</hi> no <hi>Proſperity. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycrates,</hi> Tyrant of <hi>Samos,</hi> was ſo fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate all his life, he never taſted grief o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loſs: howbeit, to partake ſome ſorrow with others, he caſt a Ring of an ineſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mable value into the Sea; which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards was found in a Fiſhes belly, and preſented him by a poor Fiſherman<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> notwithſtanding which probable eterna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>felicity,</hi> a <hi>Gibbet</hi> help'd to ſhorten hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> days. Yet ſome there are, whom (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> muſt pity, not inveigh againſt) the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent blaſts of croſs accidents hath blowt down; they would pay every man hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own but cannot. Of theſe I muſt hold with St. <hi>Auguſtine, It is not to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered what they do, as with what mind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Theſe are thoſe <hi>broken</hi> ones, into who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Charity</hi> muſt pour the balm of comfort they have <hi>broken eſtates,</hi> and <hi>brok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hearts.</hi> To bring up ſome ſolace a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> praiſe, which the Ancients have faſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to themſelves, by misfortunes; let n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> be diſheartned becauſe of <hi>Poverty,</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> entertain it with a fatal voluntar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and a hope ſtill for better; f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> aſſures them, <hi>A juſt man f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſeven times, and riſeth again,</hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 24.16. If this comfort avails little, the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:32480:23"/>let them ruminate on the Honour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd by the <hi>Romans</hi> of old on the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites of <hi>Poverty,</hi> which <hi>Nearneſs</hi> once laid aſide, they confeſs to be the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their woes. <hi>Ariſtides</hi> the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, Fabritius</hi> and <hi>Publicola Romans,</hi> had been aſſoon forgotten i'th' minde, as eye, if their mean and hard kinde of life had not made an impreſſion very deep in the memories of their Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who once accounted it the pitch of <hi>Vertue,</hi> not to indulge their carcaſſes, or live up to the allowance of <hi>Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tenthly, The laſt way of <hi>deceit,</hi> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling under my diſcourſe, is the inhanſing and raiſing the price of Commodities <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove meaſure;</hi> a thing condemn'd by <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero,</hi> though inſpir'd onely with the light of nature. If a man in time of dearth, bring a Ship laden with Corn, and know there are a great many more will in few days be up with him, if he diſſemble this, taking advantage of the preſent want, to ſell his Corn at too high a rate, he is guilty of hard and unjuſt dealing. <hi>The wicked worketh a deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful work; but to him that ſoweth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, ſhall be a ſure reward,</hi> Prov. 11.18.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:32480:24"/>
               <p>Now a Conſideration of what caſes leſſen and raiſe the price, doth here offer it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A Commodity may be worth more being ſold to one man than to another; For if our Commodities be ſold cheap without reſpect of perſons, <hi>Forraigners</hi> in other Countries may afford them as cheap as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant: and this way hath caus'd a decay in ſeveral Places of our Trade by Natives.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Commodity increaſeth its price, victuals or houſhold-proviſion being dear; otherwiſe thouſands of Artificers and Handicrafts-men muſt fare the worſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When Buyers ſeek Wares, they or a ſort of them being ſcarce, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon eſtimation being increaſed, the price may be raiſed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Commodities retailed muſt be de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rer than thoſe ſold by whoſe ſale; t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> labour and care in ſelling them thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greater: not to do ſo, is to under value the labour and care of the who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> profeſſion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Laſtly, Commodities may be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> dearer for time than ready money: Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is a perpetual eſtranging of the <hi>properly</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:32480:24"/>from the <hi>price.</hi> But that, that price ſhould be eſtranged for a time, is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the moſt ancient or true way; it ſhould be paid upon receipt of the Wares: which ſo paid may by <hi>Induſtry</hi> be increas'd; not paid, thence follows a ſenſible want of what might have been gained; which the <hi>Buyer</hi> in Conſcience ought to recompence, and the <hi>Seller</hi> may take if his Cuſtomer be not poor, or a loſer by the Wares thus bought. I have heard and read words againſt this, but not arguments.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The price is to be leſſened when a man hath fooliſhly bought his Wares; for it may happen, that he may ſell them cheaper then he bought them, and yet do <hi>unjuſtly:</hi> or if the worth of his Commodities falls after his buying them, then the <hi>price</hi> is to be leſſened.</p>
               <p>Secondly, When one ſells a <hi>great deal</hi> together, here the manner of ſelling leſſening the number of <hi>buyers,</hi> but aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting his <hi>takings,</hi> abates the <hi>price;</hi> and giving thus occaſion of ſelling them again, they muſt be ſold cheaper, leſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands, as it may fall out, <hi>ſuffer</hi> in buying them at too <hi>dear</hi> a rate.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:32480:25"/>
               <p>Thirdly, When Wares ſeek <hi>buyers</hi> (according to our Proverb) <hi>proffered Ware grows cheap;</hi> yet this is no ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent reaſon of leſſening the price, unleſs the thing thus ſold be little profitable to the <hi>Buyer,</hi> or ſuch as he would not buy, or buying it rather reſpecting the <hi>Seller</hi> than himſelf.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, When a Commodity proves faulty, or is any ways periſh'd in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or circumſtance, the price is to be leſſened. I might inſiſt upon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in a larger manner; but let this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: all <hi>Contracts</hi> muſt tend to the good of thoſe that make them; So ſhall <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice</hi> be avoided. That my <hi>Citize<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> may do ſo, I deſire that he may never forget that God is <hi>All eye,</hi> and ſo muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> behold all his actions. There is a Figure in <hi>Rhetorick</hi> reſolving many queſtion with one anſwer, which St. <hi>Baſil</hi> uſeth thus: his Diſciples ſought amongſt the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> who was oftneſt <hi>angry?</hi> who was <hi>ſlow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to <hi>divine ſervice?</hi> whoſe <hi>minde</hi> wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred moſt at <hi>prayers?</hi> He anſwered all a once thus; <hi>He that doth not always thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God to be the Spectatour of all his action.</hi> So if it be demanded, who is a <hi>Flatter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, Lyer, Diſſembler,</hi> and a <hi>Deceitful</hi> perſon
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32480:25"/>I anſwer, <hi>He who thinks not that God takes notice of his doings.</hi> He who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members this, will live <hi>juſtly;</hi> and that God which ſees him do ſo, hath a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing for him. <hi>The Righteous is delivered out of trouble, and the wicked cometh in his ſtead,</hi> Prov. 11.8. Surely in the flood of many waters they ſhall not come neer him; he will draw him out of many wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as he did <hi>Moſes;</hi> he will keep him ſafe in the midſt of many waters, as he did <hi>Jonas;</hi> ſo trouble ſhall not hurt him, he and his ſeed after him ſhall proſper.</p>
               <p>But <hi>unjuſt</hi> wicked deceitful ways are ſo common, as I muſt for a while ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of <hi>bleſſings: Mercy</hi> go aſide, <hi>Peace</hi> return to the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> and not be ſpoken of. There is <hi>judgment</hi> with thee <hi>O Lord;</hi> with thee there is <hi>ruine</hi> and <hi>ſubverſion, battel</hi> and <hi>famine, ſnares</hi> and <hi>plagues, ſtorms</hi> and <hi>tempeſts, fire</hi> and <hi>brimſtone;</hi> and therefore thou ſhalt be <hi>feared.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 95.10</note> Above forty years long haſt thou been grieved with this generation, who have erred in their hearts, and not known thy ways, that thou haſt been forc'd to puniſh it; ſtill art caus'd to complain of it, and that daily by thy <hi>Miniſters,</hi> that the noyſe is uttered from
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32480:26"/>them with grievous ſighs: but if any oppreſs thee thus, it ſhall not be <hi>London,</hi> for whom thy mercy hath done ſo much, that they are quieter in their houſes than their Enemies in their Caſtles; they have many <hi>Conduits</hi> to convey comfort to their ſouls, which others wander many leagues for. Thy mercies towards them are new and ſtrange. If <hi>God</hi> be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder,</hi> as our vileneſs is too ponderous for his patience, which is no fit place for his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> methinks he ſhould not be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you of London.</hi> I therefore ſpeak from the mouth of <hi>David;</hi> for <hi>my words</hi> will not be regarded. <hi>God turns a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Land to barrenneſ,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.</note> for the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of them that dwell therein;</hi> and from St. <hi>Auguſtine, The ruine of a City is not wrought by the Walls weakneſs, but the Citizens wickedneſs. Livy</hi> obſerves, that <hi>Rome</hi> began to loſe all, when ſin aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded amongſt all. In <hi>Gellius,</hi> mention is made of <hi>Sejus, Sejanus</hi> his Horſe, who though handſome and brave to look on, yet whoever kept him was unfortunate: Such is <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> fair to the eye, but the practiſes of it ſeldom proſper. The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy is within the Walls; this Enemy is <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> but ſhall that be found in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32480:26"/>
                  <hi>Sion?</hi> If the ſame things be there that were in <hi>Sodom,</hi> How then? ſhall not <hi>God</hi> do to one <hi>City</hi> as to another? Or ſhall there be any difference between one and tother? but that it ſhall be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier in the day of judgment, for them of <hi>Sodom</hi> than them of <hi>Sion?</hi> The more grace <hi>Sion,</hi> the more grace <hi>London</hi> hath receiv'd; the more fearfully for their ſins ſhall her inhabitants be puniſh'd and tormented. But leſt I be cenſur'd for putting my Sickle into the <hi>Divines</hi> Harveſt, I turn this Diſcourſe into <hi>Prayer, beſeeching God to guide my Citizen ſo in the way of Juſtice, that he may follow him that ſaid, I am the truth:</hi> Let him indeavour to be with him <hi>truth</hi> in words, not knowing how to be deceived; <hi>truth</hi> in deeds, conforming his actions to the <hi>Divine will,</hi> teaching him thus which is the <hi>truth,</hi> he follows him which is the <hi>way</hi> too, and that <hi>Way</hi> which leads to <hi>life,</hi> to a good one here, and a better hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The path of the juſt is as a ſhining Light,
<note place="margin">Pro. 4.18.</note> that ſhineth more and more unto the perfect day.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:32480:27"/>
               <head>Of living delightfully to himſelf.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THales</hi> one of the ſeven Sages being aſked wherein conſiſted mans trueſt happineſs, anſwered, In a <hi>ſound Body, a full Purſe, and a minde neither ſluggiſh or unpliſhed.</hi> Yet how can my <hi>Citizen</hi> live delightfully, when Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy profeſſes <hi>ſorrow</hi> to be natural to all conditions, but <hi>pleaſure</hi> to be a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? The parts capable of delight, can receive but one or two ſorts at once, but grief can affect all parts. Man hath no continuance in pleaſure, it quickly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth. He taſts of felicity, but drinks deep of miſery, according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb: <hi>Evil comes by pounds, but goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by ounces.</hi> The beſt State of this life hath been ſo undervalued, as wiſe men have ſaid, <hi>Had man been worthy to have known what life was before he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, he would have been loth to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it.</hi> This made <hi>Seneca</hi> that wiſe <hi>Roman</hi> even to hug death, as his Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer from pain and perplexity, ſaying, as he bled to death, <hi>With a Pen-knife is
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:32480:27"/>the way opened to that great liberty. Happy is that death</hi> (ſaith the ſame,) <hi>that extinguiſhes the evils of this life.</hi> The <hi>Mexicans</hi> of <hi>India</hi> thus ſalute their Children coming forth of the womb: <hi>Infant, thou art come into the World to ſuffer; ſuffer, and hold thy peace.</hi> They obſerved the condition of all men to be full of trouble; and I obſerve a <hi>Citizens</hi> condition to be extraordinary full of trouble. As no man hath <hi>pleaſure</hi> and <hi>profit</hi> without the price of ſome evil; ſo he pays a greater rate for them than moſt men do. God makes men his Balls; but of theſe Balls, who is toſt more up and down than a <hi>Citizen?</hi> He never reſts, and thus his ſtate ſeems miſerable. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and life are twins, which increaſe, are nouriſhed, and live together. We are taught out of holy Writ, that <hi>the days of man are few, and full of miſery.</hi> But Cuſtome makes things natural. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Milk-ſop can ſwim in hot Baths; though he is moſt man, can endure vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent tides, and ſtill ſwim aloft. To arm my Reader againſt the feeling and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling under adverſity, I ſhall inſtance a few examples, as more impreſſive than Precepts. <hi>Judas Macchabeus</hi> amongſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:32480:28"/>22000 men being councelled to flie; <hi>God forbid</hi> (reply'd he) <hi>that the Sun ſhould ſee me flie; I had rather die than ſtain my glory by an ignominious ſlight.</hi> Danger and neceſſity could in no wiſe overtop the ſtrength of his minde, foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the aid of an <hi>Almighty God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The very Heathens have tranſmitted to us examples of <hi>continence, temperance</hi> and <hi>patience,</hi> as reaches the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Morality; and but altering the Perſons worſhip'd, they muſt needs ſtir us up to tread their ſteps, who have walked ſo contented in all conditions. <hi>Cato</hi> the Elder was wont to ſay, <hi>Nor Houſe, nor Plate, nor Rayment, nor Man or Maid-Servant, is precious or eſteemed by me. What I have, I uſe; if I want, it is all one with me, as if I enjoy'd.</hi> Is not <hi>Cato</hi> the younger to be admired<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> who travelling the vaſt Deſarts of <hi>Lybia</hi> and labouring under extream thirſt, when a Souldier offered him Water, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his motion, he threw it on the ground, ſaying, <hi>he would fare no better than the reſt of the Army. Darius</hi> King of <hi>Perſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> is recorded by <hi>Herodotus</hi> to have m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all croſſes and miſadventures with mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and patience. <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32480:28"/>Philoſopher, when one brought him word that his Son was dead; <hi>I knew</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that I had begot a mortal man.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>Lycurgus</hi> the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Lawgiver, having power to puniſh one who had cauſed to him the loſs of an eye, contrary to opinion, diſmiſt him, and pardoned the offence. By which fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Examples, if my Reader be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing mov'd, and ſtudy not to ſhape his minde to an equal reſenting of all accidents and unfortunate chances; he will deſerve the title either of a negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, an ignorant, or an impotent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; like the <hi>Sluggard Solomon</hi> deſcribes, <hi>whoſe deſire kills him;
<note place="margin">Pro. 21.25 19.15.26.16.</note> Who is caſt into a deep ſleep; Who is wiſer than ſeven men in his own conceit; Who turneth upon his bed, and in his buſineſs, as a dore on the hinges:</hi> and finally,
<note place="margin">2.14. Eccl. 9.16. Prov. 24.7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>is void of that Wiſdome, which is better than ſtrength, or riches; and is too high for a fool.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have entred the City, where we muſt live by the Laws, and deſire free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from all trouble; yet that my Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen may be help'd with his own en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to allay the furiouſneſs of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, I preſent to his Conſideration theſe following Rules.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:32480:29"/>
               <p>Firſt, He ought to look into his <hi>Trade</hi> circumſpectly and exactly, as a true un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding thereof requires, leſt he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur <hi>Solomons</hi> cenſure;
<note place="margin">Pro. 19.2</note> as <hi>having a Soul without knowledge: and as the Fool, who hath no heart to what he hath a price in his hand for;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">17.16.</note> ſo leſt he ſlight, and take no delight in his buſineſs.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It is expedient for him to have ſufficient ſkill in Arithmetick, and a right way of keeping his Shop-Books; by which, great trading and retailing may be drawn into a little compaſs; bringing about with delight, what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture produces not without much pain and vexation.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Let him not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e himſelf too ſtrictly to any thing beyond Nature: proceedings are pleaſant, and run ſmooth with the ſtream; but if cut croſs the grain, are rough and ill ſhapen; beſide the diſturbance they cauſe in the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempters. 'Tis <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaying, <hi>The it's worth the time to obſerve, what goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> offices Wiſdom doth to thoſe whoſe deſires ſhe ſquareth.
<note place="margin">Pro. 8.12.</note> I Wiſdom</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) dwell with Prudence, and finde o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of witty Inventions.</hi> If he woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtudy the liberal Arts, let him do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:32480:29"/>ſuperficially, ſo as not to be ſwallowed up of them. Take <hi>Solomons</hi> counſel, <hi>Through deſire a man ſeparateth himſelf,
<note place="margin">Pro. 18.18</note> ſeeketh and intermedleth with all wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> But to qualifie the too inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiveneſs of any, ſee how he moderates his former encouragement, by ſaying,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 1.18.</note> 
                  <hi>In much wiſdom is much grief; and he that increaſeth knowledge increaſeth ſorrow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of all <hi>Republicks, that</hi> built by <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curgus</hi> the <hi>Lacedemonian,</hi> was the beſt, which often overcame <hi>Athens;</hi> yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver boaſted of Learning. It's remarque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able that <hi>Rome,</hi> for the firſt five hundred years flouriſh'd through <hi>Vertue,</hi> not Learning; Whereas now it decays; its <hi>Religion</hi> and immoderate <hi>Learning</hi> quite razing out Vertue. Has not this Age produced thoſe who comprehended <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> in their heads, yet have been very irregular in their perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances? <hi>Policy</hi> when natural, works free and quietly, and is without noyſe; whilſt the contrary ſends out little ſave clamour and confuſion. I ſpeak not againſt Learning; for a Citizen may uſe her, if ſhe be not imperious: but <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion</hi> (I dare affirm) is above Learning, and ſufficiently inables a man to improve
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:32480:30"/>himſelf in all his affairs; whatever he or has, is put forth to the beſt adva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tage. <hi>Learning</hi> lies in contemplation <hi>Prudence</hi> in buſineſs and action. 'T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neither Wit, Learning, Arts liberal, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mechanique, but <hi>that</hi> which ſhews ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to govern them all conveniently, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> every other thing with them; like <hi>Iph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> the <hi>Athenian,</hi> who was neith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Legionary, Souldier, Archer or Targ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> teer, but one who could govern an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Command all theſe.</p>
               <p>Again, let him not have too gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> care of the future. Future things i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time become preſent; therefore theca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of preſent ſufficeth. <hi>Commit thy wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> unto the Lord, and thy thoughts ſhall eſtabliſhed,</hi> Prov. 16.3. It was ſaid firſt, <hi>In the ſweat of thy brows thou ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eat thy bread.</hi> He did not ſay (ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> St. <hi>Auguſtine)</hi> in <hi>ſolitude</hi> and <hi>care;</hi> ought to be <hi>heedful,</hi> but we muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ware, leſt we be tainted with <hi>Covetouſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> A good Biſhop could have preach'd gainſt this vice an hour together, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing, but <hi>Beware of covetouſneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> a wonder to ſee what anxious thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men have for the World, which is <hi>bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and yet 'tis loved: but how would it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:32480:30"/>loved, if it became wholly <hi>ſweet?</hi> What extream care do ſome men take to heap up wealth! <hi>Caligula</hi> Emperour of <hi>Rome</hi> was ſo Covetous, as beſides the hundred ways he had to bring in the blood of his Subjects, he laid an Impoſt on Urine; nay, ſold his Siſters Gowns, and other Attires, after he had baniſh'd them. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipha</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> for his Avarice, and exceſſive oppreſſions to fill his Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, being forſaken of his Subjects when he ſtood in need of their aid againſt his Enemies, was forc'd to retire himſelf into a ſtrong Caſtle, where his heart was cheſted, and wherein lay all his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity; there (like <hi>Minos</hi> King of <hi>Creet)</hi> ſtarving, becauſe what ere he touch'd was Gold, which miniſtred little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to his pining and languiſhing body. <hi>Her mocrates</hi> a <hi>Grecian Philoſopher,</hi> dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, bequeath'd all his Eſtate to himſelf, his minde being fix'd immovably on the traſh he had ſcraped together. <hi>Cardinal Angelot</hi> was ſo wrapt up in covetouſneſs, as by a trap-dore to get into his Stable, and to ſteal the Corn his <hi>Groom</hi> had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his Horſes. O the blindneſs of mans judgment, and what poyſon incloſes and ſhoots forth of this Root of all evil!
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:32480:31"/>
                  <hi>Epimenides</hi> the Philoſopher wiſh'd, <hi>The a Prodigal might inherit the means of very Covetous perſon.</hi> The foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Lycurgus</hi> baniſh'd the uſe of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Silver from <hi>Lacedemon,</hi> Iron-mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being only currant and allow'd of, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by taking away the cauſe of coveto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neſs. I'm ſure this reſtleſneſs in the pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuit, and plotting how to get wealt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is not ſucceſsful; for Divine Providen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will not be bound by our proviſions thoſe have been <hi>ſtilleſt</hi> and moſt <hi>proſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,</hi> who readily apprehended the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſent opportunity with <hi>chearfulneſs.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> man may be careful for to morrow wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> content.
<note place="margin">Prov. 23.4</note> 
                  <hi>Labour not to be rich</hi> (ſays <hi>Sol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) ceaſe from thy own underſtandin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Riches are not for ever.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">27.24.</note> However, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ligence is not pleaded for, in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> monition againſt <hi>riches,</hi> but the wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> uſe of them; it is a defect: and <hi>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> laboureth,
<note place="margin">16.26.</note> laboureth for himſelf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> mouth craveth it of him.</hi> To dwell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> long in deliberation is exceſs; for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Slothful is brother to the Waſter.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">18.9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>As the Emperour would add City City, Country to Country, and Nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to Nation; ſo men ſtrive to joyn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dreds to hundreds, and thouſands
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:32480:31"/>thouſands, thinking to reſt when they have but compaſſed their ends. Oh Fools! they may do ſo before if they will; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man is rich, if his mind hinder not. <hi>There is</hi> (ſaith the Wiſeman) <hi>a man to whom God hath given riches,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 24.4</note> wealth and honour, ſo that he wanteth nothing for his ſoul of all he deſireth; yet God giveth him not power to eat thereof, but a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger eateth it; this is vanity of an evil diſeaſe.
<note place="margin">Prov. 23.5.</note> Wilt thou ſet thine eyes upon that which hath wings, upon that which profiteth not in the day of wrath?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">11.4.</note> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, it is every ones duty to pray not to enter into this temptation; <hi>For he that truſteth to his riches ſhall fall;
<note place="margin">11.28.</note> but the Righteous ſhall ſtouriſh as a branch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will bring up the rear with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample or two, of the further contempt of unbounded wealth, at leaſt its nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardly enjoyment. <hi>Fabritius</hi> the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> being ſent Ambaſſadour to King <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> his renowned actions had ſo gained the Kings affections by mere fame, as he offered him half his Dominions to ſerve him. But <hi>Fabritius</hi> gallantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed his proffer, as being diſhonourable for a <hi>Romane,</hi> and not ſuiting with <hi>his</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who lived (though a Heathen) as if
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:32480:32"/>he was to die each morrow. <hi>Solon</hi> (one of the ſeven wiſemen) deſired riches, but <hi>by juſt ways, and to the injury of none. Socrates</hi> being ſent for by <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelaus</hi> King of <hi>Cappadocia</hi> to come and live in pomp and ſplendour, returned him this anſwer, that <hi>a meaſure of flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> was ſold in</hi> Athens <hi>for two pence, and water coſt him nothing.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>There is nothing better for a man,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 2.22.</note> than that he ſhould eat and drink, and that he ſhould make his ſoul injoy good in his labour;</hi> and ſo <hi>the Lord give thee neither poverty or riches.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 30.8</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, All things which we ſufie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are by our opinion made greater: the are more things fright than hurt us ſome trouble us more than they ſhould ſome before they ſhould, and for which ſhould not at all. It is ſtrange <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> conſider moſt of our diſturbances to riſe from ſuch ſmall cauſes, and that a cidents ſhould touch us more than t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> principal. <hi>Caeſars</hi> robe more mov'd <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> than his 22 ſtabs; and leſſer circumſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſtir us more many times than the ſubject themſelves. In what hath been ſpoke, we are as miſerable as we think o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelves.
<note place="margin">Pro. 29.25</note> 
                  <hi>The fear of a man bringeth a ſna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:32480:32"/>It becometh a wiſe man to be heedful, not fearful; for baſe fear bringeth double danger,</hi> ſays <hi>Vigetius. Dionyſius</hi> the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant was ſo fearful, that rather than truſt the Barbers Razor, he ſindged his Beard with Coals. <hi>Valienus</hi> a <hi>Romane,</hi> cut off the Fingers of his left hand, rather than to follow the Wars in <hi>Italy.</hi> The Emperour <hi>Claudius</hi> was ſo faint-hearted, baſe-minded and blockiſh, as cauſed his own Mother to ſay often, <hi>Nature had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, but not finiſh'd him;</hi> wherein we may behold the uglineſs of a paſſion ſo low. Quite contrary, how quietly might we live, if when being diſturb'd we help reaſon to the upper hand, and weigh well what we put in act? Let <hi>Marcus Aurclius</hi> perſwade you to throw off fear, who had neither Guard nor Porter. <hi>Dangers</hi> ſometimes are like <hi>Crocodiles,</hi> who if purſu'd, flie; but if fled from are emboldned to follow. If any kinde of <hi>Fear</hi> is ſuffered to abide with you, let it be <hi>that</hi> which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro</hi> 10.27.14.27.15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Prolongeth days; is the fountain of life, is the inſeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of wiſdome, * keepeth the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and is the riches and honour of Life:</hi> all which vertues are comprehe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſolely in him, who can and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:32480:33"/>penſe his graces to thoſe who humbly beg them of him, and is our only <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent Lord</hi> and <hi>Creatour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, 'Tis ordinary for a <hi>Citizen</hi> to <hi>truſt,</hi> and he commonly loſeth much by it. I think there is no <hi>Citizen,</hi> nor ever was, can or could boaſt of his get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings by <hi>all</hi> he dealt withal. <hi>Democri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> the Philoſopher promiſed to revive <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his dead friend, upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, that the Inſcription of his Tomb might be the name of thirty men, who had lived to the twentieth year of their age without grief. They ſought thirty, but found none. I might promiſe the like impoſſibility, upon Condition that I might ſee the names of thirty <hi>Citizens,</hi> which have traded twenty, nay ten years, whoſe Books are without ſome Debts they never hope to be diſcharged. But what of that! Why doſt thou wonder that good men are ſmitten to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd?
<note place="margin">Pro. 10.29 24.10.</note> 
                  <hi>when the way of the Lord is ſtrength. If thou faint in the days of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, thy ſtrength is but ſmall,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi> Our Saviour ſhewed his glory in Mount <hi>Tabor</hi> but to three, and thoſe his <hi>Apoſtles:</hi> But why was there no Centurion, no Publican, or not all the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:32480:33"/>
                  <hi>ſtles?</hi> There was a world of people ſaw him on the <hi>Croſs;</hi> and good reaſon for't, (ſaith one) <hi>Proſperity ſcarce profits any.</hi> The <hi>Croſs</hi> and <hi>affliction</hi> doth many good; and therefore <hi>Bonaventure</hi> ſaid, <hi>he had rather go with Chriſt to</hi> Golgotha <hi>than to</hi> Tabor. Shall a man be weary of his life, becauſe it is accompanied with trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and loſſes? no, our Saviour (our Head) was crown'd with Thorns. Oh! how ill do delicate Members agree with a Thorny head! When <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> and others his Souldiers and Citizens of <hi>Rome,</hi> wore Garlands, to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie publickly their joy; one of them a Chriſtian wore his Crown on his arm, not head, (ſaying) <hi>That it did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Chriſtian to be crown'd in this life.</hi> Patiently ſhould that be born, which no ſtrength can overcome, nor counſel avoid, whether body and mind be afflicted by it. A man can't be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways on the gaining hand; however, it declares a great deal of weakneſs and folly to vex, and fret, and debar himſelf or reſt, when his very tears can't recal or reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the loſs. We may amend our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in dealing; but to make them not to be any more, requires more than
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:32480:34"/>Mortality can produce. Actions <hi>past</hi> may admit a correction, not a nullity. Why then ſhould loſs ſeparate a man from his heart? <hi>He that hath himſelf</hi> (ſaith a Wiſeman) <hi>hath all things.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a ltttle more what ſenſe the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents had of croſſes and Adverſity. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> counſel'd to revenge a wrong, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, <hi>What if a Maſtiff had bit me, or an Aſs had kick'd me, would you have me to go to law with them? Mauritius</hi> Emperour of the Weſt, beholding his Children put to death before his eyes, when he ſaw his Wife alſo ſuffer, onely cried out, <hi>Oh Lord, thou art juſt, and thy judgments are right. Euſebius</hi> being wounded to death with a Stone thrown at him by an <hi>Arrian</hi> woman, was ſo far from ſtorming and revenge, as he ſwore all his Friends not to puniſh her after his death. <hi>Harpalus</hi> being invited by <hi>Aſtyages</hi> King of <hi>Media</hi> to ſupper, where two of his Children were cook'd for him inſtead of Veniſon, without the leaſt Marks of aſtoniſhment he beheld a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle, able to have drawn water and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment from a heart leſs Rocky and Prudent.</p>
               <p>I muſt acknowledge my <hi>Citizens</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:32480:34"/>and fortitude of minde to be ſcrew'd up to the height, when he is dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the neceſſity of <hi>breaking,</hi> after he has ſtriven it may be to fetch <hi>fire out of wood,</hi> and to reſiſt the <hi>Decree of Divine Providence:</hi> yet it is doubtful, whether he hath not neglected ſome means, been an <hi>ill husband,</hi> and ſpent too much time and money in vain. Let him take my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice before my comfort; I would have him, though he leave himſelf not worth a groat, to pay every one his own: or if he compounds to pay a part, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs let him reſolve to ſatisfie all to the full, if his endeavours and Gods bleſſing ever again enables him. This is his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, by ſuffering he ſhall conquer. The <hi>Romans</hi> overcame ſitting ſtill: his ſoul, becauſe his intentions are ſincere, will be void of it anxiety and repining; and by how much he is more quiet, by ſo much the ſtronger. Great aſperſions lie on his name, his ſpirits are dampt, and almoſt ſtifled with grief. Let him apply <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Mauritius</hi> their Medicine. A Poor, yet the wiſeſt of <hi>Grecians,</hi> was ſlandered, and an unfortunate Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour found comfort in the horrid A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonies of Cruelty. His bleſſings were
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:32480:35"/>of the Lord, how then can he want, that by patience holds faſt him that gave him all? who hath taken from him with <hi>Job</hi> to ſeaſon him, and make him afterwards more thankfully to abound in plenty. What <hi>Cain</hi> ſaid of his ſins, <hi>They are grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than can be forgiven,</hi> no Chriſtian may ſay of his loſſes, <hi>Greater then can be reſtor'd.</hi> 'Tis impious to imagine <hi>Jobs God</hi> not to retain his Omnipotency and Mercy for thoſe who ſeek him with a pure and uncorrupt heart. Conſider onely <hi>Jobs</hi> beginning and ending: Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he never ſaw <hi>Fortunes</hi> double face before: <hi>Providence</hi> permits him to be try'd by <hi>Adverſity</hi> for his experience and improvement of wiſdome. Tribulation refines the underſtanding: We grow wiſe by blows. <hi>Hannibal</hi> deſervedly boaſted of himſelf: <hi>Age, Proſperity and Adverſity have ſo inſtructed me, that I had rather follow Reaſon than Fortune.</hi> He had never attain'd this pitch of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, had not his declining Fortunes obliged him to ſurmount all difficulties by his conduct. My experience amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting not to above ſeven years, hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd me with examples in this <hi>City,</hi> of ſome who have ſunk for all a good <hi>Stock</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:32480:35"/>and <hi>Trade,</hi> into nothing comparatively; and of others whoſe ſmall beginnings have riſen to vaſt and incredible Eſtates. Whoſe advancement and their likely cauſes, is fit for thee to inquire into. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> thanked God for being born a <hi>man,</hi> not a <hi>woman;</hi> a <hi>Grecian,</hi> not a <hi>Barbarian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and for not being <hi>unlearned,</hi> eſteeming the Gifts of Nature and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to be contemptible, if not beautified with the Ornaments of the Minde. He was a wiſe King that would be pictur'd ſwimming, with this Motto: <hi>I ſtrive, I am not drowned.</hi> And <hi>Chabot</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Admiral of <hi>France</hi> would be ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliz'd by a Ball, with this Inſcription: <hi>Being ſmitten, Iriſe higher.</hi> But above all Examples take this: Our Saviour calling to <hi>Saul,</hi> ſaid, <hi>Ariſe, and ſtand upon thy feet.</hi> As if he had ſaid (writes one) <hi>I have caſt thee down, to the intent that thou maiſt riſe ſtronger.</hi> And it was the voice of that great Apoſtle; <hi>When I am weakned, I then grow mighty.</hi> This I ſpeak to comfort his ſoul, and to help him forward in bettering his <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> even as his Eſtate. Men in Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity are ſeldom <hi>Religious.</hi> He therefore and onely he gets, by his <hi>breaking,</hi> who
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:32480:36"/>is more <hi>humble, pitiful, mortified, given to prayer,</hi> and the <hi>like duties:</hi> doing thus, if <hi>Poor</hi> without, he is <hi>Rich</hi> within; He hath <hi>that</hi> within him, whereof he may rejoyce. Our Wealth and Gold is <hi>Chriſt;</hi> come to him, and you ſhall abound with true riches. He now flings off his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer careleſs way, and finds God before angry, now to be kinde: Nothing ſave his treſpaſſes, could keep off Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; now nothing but a continued ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious repentance blots out ſinning; which repentance, I adviſe may not fall ſhort, but reach out far as the bleſſings expected; for that falls not on the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance but <hi>exit</hi> of a ſpiritual grace; he onely that endures to the end ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Crown. Nothing can lay claim to the eternal benedictions of God, but perſeverance, which is mans <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> If thou wouldſt then extract ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual from the loſs of temporal bleſſings; if thou wouldſt by <hi>Jacobs Ladder</hi> climb from all that's Terreſtrial and Earthy, which is its foot, to all that's Celeſtial and Heavenly, which is its top; Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber upon that Ladder Angels were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending and deſcending, but none ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtill: therefore perſiſt, and leave
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:32480:36"/>not. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells thee,
<note place="margin">Prov. 10.8</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord will not ſuffer the Righteous to famiſh; but he caſteth away the ſubſtance of the wicked. The Righteous ſhall never be removed.
<note place="margin">10.30.13.6.</note> Righteouſneſs keepeth him that is upright in the way; and is better than great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, To conclude; if he would live in true delight, let him become a Son of the Church, and increaſe daily in piety towards his Creatour: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes him not to have his <hi>Bible</hi> in his Houſe more for ornament than uſe. Let him ſtudy Divinity, yet ſo, <hi>As the Prieſts lips may</hi> be ſaid to <hi>preſerve knowledge.</hi> 'Tis the fault of theſe times, to make <hi>that</hi> their own and others <hi>deſtruction,</hi> which ſhould be their <hi>ſolace,</hi> by miſtaking <hi>Schiſm</hi> for true Religion. They would not run from Religion to Superſtition, yet how they hurry to prophaneſs. Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Schiſm are both bad; the one erects an abſolute Tyranny over mens minds, the other gives way to all looſneſs. He was a wiſe Statiſt, that ſaid,
<note place="margin">Papiſts call the true way Were<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, the Start-ups Formality.</note> 
                  <hi>He had rather have a man an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theist than either, becauſe he ſeldome diſturbs States, and is alwaies very wary.</hi> But to our purpoſe: let his Religion
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:32480:37"/>teach him to have his ſoul ſtill panting after Heaven, ſtealing up thither in the midſt of buſineſs, as if he was ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing in a place, whence he looks for his <hi>Saviour. It is better</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) to go to the houſe of mourning,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.2.</note> than to the houſe of feaſting. The fear of the Lord is ſtrong confidence,
<note place="margin">Pro. 14.26</note> and his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhall have a place of refuge.
<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.13</note> To fear God and keep his Commandments is the whole duty of Man.</hi> King <hi>Alfred</hi> is recorded to have divided the day and night into three parts; eight hours he allotted to eat and ſleep in, eight to buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and recreation, and eight he dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſtudy, meditation and prayer. How happy ſhould we all be, if we could form our life by ſuch a Pattern! Certainly the repentance of moſt <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> comes too late: For it's rare to ſee a Shopkee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to break any hours of reſt, to ſerve his God, or ſo much as to prize an hour in his Worſhip, before the diſpatch of the moſt frivolous matters. Let the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of our Glorious King and Martyr <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Firſt, quicken the deadneſs of my <hi>Citizens</hi> zeal. For our Pious Prince could ſeldome be turn'd from his conſtancy in prayers and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:32480:37"/>whereof his incomparable Books give ſufficient Teſtimony. What a ſhame then is it in the higheſt degree, for a <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen</hi> whoſe concerns are petty, trivial, and of no moment, in compariſon of a Princes, to be outſtript by one, who lived in the midſt of <hi>Tumults, Diſorders, Conſpiracies,</hi> and <hi>Diſturbances?</hi> Man is made in the <hi>Earth,</hi> and of the <hi>Earth,</hi> but not for it, and to it; but <hi>to Heaven</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>and for Heaven. He,</hi> whom no buſineſs ſhould put out of our minds, <hi>is in Heaven: He is riſen, he is not here.</hi> Look for him in the Church, you ſhall have him there; look for him by invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and a Conſcionable diligence in thy Calling, and the Holy Ghoſt will ſhew him there; and when thou haſt thus found him, he will take thee up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to reign there with him. St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> and St. <hi>Jerome</hi> wonder at the <hi>Eunuch</hi> in the 8 of the <hi>Acts;</hi> He was a <hi>Barbarian</hi> diſtracted with many buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; he read, and though he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not, yet he read, and that in the way in the Chariot. If he was thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted in his journey, how would he have been in quiet at home? If he a <hi>Heathen</hi> did thus much in the way, ſhall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:32480:38"/>not we <hi>Chriſtians</hi> do more in our Shops? To minde the affair of our Soul, is the way to prevent diſtraction, and not to further it: as <hi>Phyſicians</hi> ſay of ſorrow for ſin: <hi>It hurts not the heart, as worldly ſorrow doth;</hi> So I may ſay, <hi>it is worldly care, not this, that troubles our peace.</hi> I ſhall end with <hi>Solomon;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 10.10</note> That <hi>the labour of the Righteous man tendeth to life, the fruit of the Wicked to ſin.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of pleaſing Others.</head>
               <p>IT is written of <hi>Alcibiades</hi> the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> that in what Country or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſoever he hapned to be, he could frame himſelf admirably to their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Cuſtoms and Humours. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Behaviour</hi> is much to be ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to be prized by my <hi>Citizen.</hi> It muſt needs be diſtaſtful to any man coming into a Shop, to ſee a man ſtand as if he was drown'd in flegm and pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; having no other ſigne of motion, or being awake, than that his eyes are open. The outward Carriage ſhould promiſe what's within the man; except Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:32480:38"/>
                  <hi>Courteſie</hi> is more regarded of men than any other vertue. <hi>Courteſie is a true token of Nobility, and the certain mark of a Gentleman</hi> (ſaith a Wiſe man.) <hi>Courteſie</hi> (ſaith another) <hi>draweth the love of ſtrangers, and good liking of our Country-men.</hi> It pays a great deal, yet is ne'r the poorer; it ſatisfies every man, yet leſſens not the Stock: it is a good Character of a good nature; and it hath been obſerved, that few ſurly and chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, have riſen to great Fortunes. Theſe ſmall ceremonies win larger commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, becauſe they are in continual uſe and note; whereas the occaſion for ſhewing a <hi>great vertue,</hi> preſents it ſelf but ſeldome. To be clowniſh to others, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigates them to return <hi>quid</hi> for <hi>quo,</hi> and deſtroys that reſpect which amongſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and perſons of any breeding, is a quality of worth. It is a kinde of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to be <hi>Courteous</hi> without Pride or affectation. Yet to make no difference in the uſe of it towards a Lord, or Ploughman, kiſſing their hands, and bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as low to a Chambermaid as her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, is uncomely. It was well ſaid of one, <hi>The outward deportment covers and uncovers the minde;</hi> which to ſome
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:32480:39"/>ſhould be more open, to others more hid. Let my <hi>Citizen</hi> then be Ceremonious, but without affectation, nor too often. He can't comprehend great matters, that breaks his minde too much on ſmall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations. But there is an inward thing, which, unleſs it be added to the exteriour, makes them all nothing. A Schoolmaſter had in his place of Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe a Glaſs, wherein he caus'd his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to behold themſelves. <hi>If they were Handſome, he would tell them what pity it was, ſuch goodly bodies ſhould be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with defective minds: If they were deform'd</hi> (he would tell them) <hi>they ſhould make their bodies more beautiful, with dreſſing their minds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the behaviour and countenance be good, the ornament of the minde doubles the excellency: If miſ-ſhapen and ill, parts and ingenuity will poliſh Natures roughneſs, and cauſe the greater admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>performance</hi> and <hi>promiſe</hi> being at ſuch a diſtance.</p>
               <p>His minde muſt be ſtuft with ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency to produce pleaſant Diſcourſe, wherein he muſt not laviſhly hinder his obſervation, and become tedious to him he deals with. <hi>A word fitly ſpoken, is
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:32480:39"/>like Apples of Gold in pictures of Silver,</hi> Prov. 25.11. To ſpeak all he can at once (as if he were making his Will) is not the moſt plauſible and pleaſing way; the beſt to do it, is to know how to be ſilent.
<note place="margin">Pro. 17.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Even a Fool when he holdeth his peace</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) is counted wiſe, and he that ſhutteth his lips is eſteemed a man of underſtanding.</hi> When he ſpeaks, let it not be with vehemence. His words ſhould flow from his mouth, ſo that it might be ſaid of them, <hi>They are not ſo much Words as Honey. Pleaſant words</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi> again) <hi>are as a Honey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb, ſweet to the Soul,
<note place="margin">Pro. 16.24</note> and health to the bones.</hi> I would have ſuch words uſed in his Commerce; for therein his Cuſtomer, will commonly take more delight to hear, than he to ſpeak. All he ſpeaks muſt be true: however the Dreſs be, Truth is conſtantly the ſame; it ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the ſame ſplendour; and if it meets with a maſculine, and not a whining utterance, fitted to matter and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, is praiſe-worthy: beſides, it gives more grace &amp; luſtre to the Speech, than poſſibly it can borrow from it. <hi>The tongue of the wiſe, uſeth knowledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right;
<note place="margin">Pro. 15.2.</note> but the mouth of Fools poureth out
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:32480:40"/>fooliſhneſs.</hi> Becauſe moſt men are taken with ſmooth language, let words be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly choſen, and properly applied; for as Speech makes a man more excellent than a Beaſt, ſo Eloquence intitles him to a preference before other men: but to this muſt be added a grave natural action, wherein a man may behold the Viſage, Hands, and Members of another to ſpeak with his Mouth; and thus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading the Cuſtomer to a <hi>liking</hi> of his Commodity, he muſt put on the ſame <hi>Liking</hi> himſelf; for by acting himſelf, that <hi>Paſſion</hi> he would ſtir up in others, he ſeldome miſſes of prevailing. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, in as much as he is to deal with Perſons of divers Diſpoſitions, he muſt accommodate his diſcourſe, as neer as he can, to the humour of the Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as being his beſt Rhetorick. I muſt needs condemn the uſing of one Phraſe or kinde of Speech to all men, the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſting of every ones Senſes, with a <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you hear Sir,</hi> and the <hi>telling of all he wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> make but a word,</hi> which are ordinary terms, but of no fineneſs or validity. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he would tell his minde at once, I wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him to do it, as being the Old and Beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> way. He that ſold <hi>Abraham</hi> the Field
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:32480:40"/>for burial, aſk'd what he would, and had it. But the cuſtome of our times is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and what is uſual is preſumed to be juſt: however, I deſire my <hi>Citizen</hi> to uſe the feweſt words he can; and it's poſſible, Time will reduce the manner of Bargaining to its firſt and beſt Rule.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not tax the common Phraſe of <hi>What lack ye?</hi> it being great Policy, for a man in that form to intreat for his own neceſſities; but the too much uſe of it ſounds harſh. I would not have a mans throat worn like a high-way; he ſhould ſtep a little out of the ordinary Road; but taking heed of the other extream, he muſt not become a wilful maker of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, and ſo a Tyrannous torment to his Cuſtomer, who will count him Impertinent, to finde him drown'd in ſuch ſuperfluous Ceremonies.</p>
               <p>To his <hi>Superiour</hi> his words muſt carry much humility, to his <hi>Equals</hi> familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſet off notwithſtanding with <hi>a mean ſtate,</hi> as requiring their <hi>notice,</hi> and not <hi>contempt. Do this now my Son</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) when thou art come into the hand of thy Friend, humble thy ſelf,
<note place="margin">Pro. 6.3.</note> and make ſure of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To his <hi>Inferiours</hi> he muſt be familiar
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:32480:41"/>too,
<note place="margin">Pro. 29.23</note> leſt <hi>Mans pride make him low;</hi> yet obſerve a diſtance, leſt he loſe his eſteem. <hi>Eſops</hi> Frogs, after they had recovered their fright, inſulted over what before they fear'd. So dreggiſh and low Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, can't prize a thing acquaintance makes them bold with: It's undeniable, but a reſerved familiarity, heightens re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation; and when Opinion ſhall uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally favour a man, Reverence never fails attendance.</p>
               <p>To conclude, my <hi>Citizen</hi> may deal pleaſingly with all men: if he hath In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity, <hi>nay but a grain,</hi> Time and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, it would advance his Credit to attain knowledge in Languages. For Learning, as it is accounted no burthen, raiſes its Pretenders in the eyes of all men, above what's meerly Wealthy: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it muſt needs contribute much to obtaining acquaintance, and purchaſing of Friends, the very Fundamentals of <hi>Trade,</hi> increaſing the poſſeſſors fame, as being Country-man to all <hi>Europeans;</hi> at leaſt to more than one Kingdom contains, Pardon me if I reflect more ſeverely on <hi>Booksellers</hi> than any other <hi>Callings:</hi> They have all the Utenſils of Learning about them, <hi>living by Learning,</hi> though
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:32480:41"/>its <hi>worth</hi> runs more into their <hi>Pockets</hi> than <hi>Heads.</hi> Juſt what value the <hi>Indians</hi> ſet upon Gold, the ſupreameſt Metal, they do on Learning and knowledge, which are <hi>precious Jewels.</hi> The <hi>Indians</hi> ſlight as traſh (becauſe 'tis very eaſie to come by,) the richeſt part of Earth, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing it for any trifles which have no more of art in them than would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Children in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> as Beads, Knives, and other ſuch like knick-nacks. <hi>Booksellers</hi> comparatively, live amidſt whatever is conducible towards poliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the chief parts of Man; and yet how few of them do (when Age ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them more conſpicuous and bright, for their parts ſuck'd out of Profit) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel other Tradeſmen? how few, I ſay are there, <hi>whoſe tongues are cloven;</hi> but exchanging their time and <hi>Books</hi> ſooner for <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Money,</hi> than imploy ſome hours (whereof God knows they have yearly a great many to ſpare) in improving their underſtandings, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Languages, Hiſtory or Divinity: which laſt two, might be by them in a large meaſure acquir'd, and that in proſecuting the attainable neceſſary and moſt uſeful Tongues. Without diligent
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:32480:42"/>reading and obſervation, Syllables are not to be diſtinctly fixed in the memory, and ſo can't be either true ſpoken or written. Whereas the advantages reſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Reading, are Matter for diſcourſe or imitation, exactneſs for expreſſion, by mouth, or pen: and above all, to <hi>kill two Birds with one Stone,</hi> when in ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting the difficulties of any Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage (whether in the Grammatical part, or a general comprehenſion of its fulneſs, that without a Dictionary an Author may be peruſed, beſides his ſkill in Phraſe, words and rules) my <hi>Citizen</hi> may collect piece by piece, enough to make a compleat armour to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt the ſtroaks of <hi>fear, fancy, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance</hi> and <hi>preſumption.</hi> Hiſtory as a Head-piece will keep his <hi>fancy</hi> from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſtrengthen his judgment by example, with-hold him from aſſenting to vulgar and irrational Stories, and arm him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the various changes of Time, the infinite caſualties, and dayly actions hapning in the World, which diſtract and diſturb the too prompt Nature of us <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Wherefore a ſmall inſpection into Hiſtory affords Paſſages and Perſons enow to compare with the like of his
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:32480:42"/>days. It is meer ignorance, and want of conſulting Books, makes the greateſt part of mankinde, to be ſo deſervedly rebuked by <hi>Solomon,</hi> with a <hi>Say not thou, What is the cauſe that the former days were better than theſe? for thou doſt not enquire wiſely concerning this,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.10. Divinity (which may be pick'd out of ſuch works, learned and pious men, nay, the general part of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde have a great kindneſs for, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of, and which a Bookſeller can't miſs, or fail of knowing;) This Divinity (eſpecially the Bible, which is the Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler) aſſures him in the Faith of his moſt zealous and godly Forefathers, makes him to cling to the unerring Principles of the <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick Church;</hi> nay, his conſtant and light viewing of the moſt famous Pieces, whereof choice can't be wanting to him, inſtils by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees into him arguments ſtrong enough to repel thoſe mighty ſhifts, his enemies in Religion may ſet afoot to ſupplant him. Ariſing in this manner in courſe of time to ſome perfection, he is capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated for Magiſtracy; or what ere his ſufficiency ſhall cauſe to be laid on him. Wiſdom thus built, and on theſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:32480:43"/>of throughly conſidering the World and its Opinions, <hi>This is better than weapons of War;
<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.18.</note> This Wiſdom is a defence,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.12.</note> and giveth life to them that have it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Self-Profit.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EVery man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Socrates) is a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of his own Fortune, faſhioning it as he pleaſes.</hi> Yet it can't be denyed, but outward accidents conduce much: as death of others, occaſion fitting vertues; but moſt commonly the folly and fall of one man, is the Fortune of another: no man proſpers ſo ſuddenly as by anothers errours &amp; unhappineſs; therefore it was imprudently done by <hi>Daemades</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn an <hi>Athenian for ſelling neceſſaries belonging to burials;</hi> ſaying, <hi>his great profit came not ſave by the death of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:</hi> for what man almoſt getteth, but by the loſs of others? Was not <hi>Rome</hi> raiſed on the ruine of her Neighbour-Cities? did <hi>Caeſar</hi> aſſume to himſelf the dignity of Emperour, till he had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:32480:43"/>or rather deſtroy'd <hi>Pompey?</hi> Have not the <hi>Turks</hi> expell'd and rooted Chriſtianity out of the chiefeſt places they have in poſſeſſion? Have not the <hi>Dutch</hi> attained almoſt an invincible ſtrength, onely by fraud, induſtry, and over-reaching all (if they could) that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they traffick'd with? do not abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance thrive, through the licentiouſneſs of Youth? the Huſbandman by dearth of Corn? Garpenters, Bricklayers and Glaſiers, by the decay and deſire of build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Houſes? the Lawyers by conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? the Phyſicians by others Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers? Yet this is not contrary to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Policy and order of Nature; for the Learned hold, <hi>That the production and augmentation of one thing, is the alteration and corruption of another.</hi> God takes from one, and gives to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but let no man deſire it; for the Commandment is, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet:</hi> there are then, and muſt be external cauſes of a mans Fortune. <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> of a Common Souldier, was choſen King of <hi>Egypt; Telophanes</hi> Chariot-maker, <hi>King of Lydia; Darius (Cyrus</hi> his Quiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer) King of <hi>Perſia; Agathocles,</hi> of a Potters Son, King of <hi>Sicily;</hi> and <hi>Tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlan</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:32480:44"/>of a Shepherd became King of the <hi>Tartars.</hi> In which we cannot but with admiration, contemplate the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency of God Almighty, who without reſpect of perſons, <hi>Pulleth down, and ſetteth up,</hi> that his moſt holy and great Name may be exalted (with confuſion of face) through the whole Earth.</p>
               <p>But there is ſome hidden vertue, which muſt bear a great ſtroak. <hi>He that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth the winde</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) ſhall not ſow;
<note place="margin">Eccl. 11.4.</note> and he that regardeth the Clouds ſhall not reap:</hi> Whereupon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments another; <hi>A Wiſeman will make more opportunities than he finds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Is the main thing then that promotes a man, and enlargeth his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes within or without him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Titus Livius</hi> tells us, <hi>Cato</hi> Senior was ſo well accompliſh'd in body and minde, that in what place ſoever he had been born, he could have raiſed the ſtructure of his own preferment. <hi>Rodol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> otherwiſe of baſe Parentage, for his Vertues ſake was choſen to that Dignity. The Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture teſtifies of many who were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd from low degree. Theſe are then open vertues which beget praiſe,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:32480:44"/>but hidden ones which bring forth preferment.</p>
               <p>Secondly, For that which is without a man (inſtead of Providence, let me call it Divine Providence) it can make him fortunate who is not wiſe; and if wiſe, miſerable. <hi>Alcibiades</hi> the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> was highly beloved of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men, meerly becauſe Nature ſhew'd ſo much perfection in him, who never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs for the greateſt part of his life was of a Luxurious and debauched diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. But <hi>Socrates,</hi> the wiſeſt of Heathens, (who hath been ſo often, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and deſervedly mentioned,) for all he had been ſo uſeful and beneficial to the aforeſaid <hi>Athenians,</hi> was through envy accuſed, and by thoſe who had received ſo much good at his hands, condemn'd to death. Examples clear e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to behold therein the blindneſs of Chance. Sometimes ſimple Men bring to paſs happily, matters both Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and Private, whilſt the beſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels have the worſt iſſues. <hi>There are</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) many devices in mans heart;
<note place="margin">Pro. 19.21.</note> but the Councel of the Lord ſhall ſtand.</hi> The ſame Councel ſucceeds, proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perouſly to ſome, unhappily to others.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:32480:45"/>Many things alike in the Caſe and to the man, that yeſterday hapned luckily, to day, fall out croſs and unfortunate; ſo that mans ſufficiency and ability is not always to be judg'd by Event. The Lord gave <hi>Solomon</hi> Wiſdom above all the Men of the Earth;
<note place="margin">Kings 3.</note> yet how did he ſwerve and go aſtray, before he died! wherein may be ſeen the pravity of Mans Nature; and how vain it is to truſt to Mortal Wiſdom. How did <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> counſel to deſtroy the <hi>Jews,</hi> light with heavy vengeance on his own head! One wondring why <hi>ill ſucceſs</hi> ſhould follow the <hi>mature deliberation</hi> of wiſe men, was anſwered thus; <hi>Every man Propoſes, but God Diſpoſes. Timotheus</hi> in the account he gave the <hi>Athenians</hi> of his warlike actions, often interlaced his ſpeech, with this ſaying, <hi>And in this Fortune had no part:</hi> but it was noted of him, that he never proſpered afterwards. <hi>Divine Providence</hi> muſt have its due; there is no riſing without it.
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1</note> 
                  <hi>There is no Power but of God. Saul</hi> from amongſt the loweſt of the People was anointed the firſt King of Iſrael;
<note place="margin">Samuel.</note> but ſinning, he was rejected of God, and died preſently after the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> had put him and his
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:32480:45"/>Army to flight. Now joyning all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>Diligence with the bleſſing of the Lord,</hi> crowns the expectation of Man.
<note place="margin">Pro. 10.22</note> 
                  <hi>The bleſſing of the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon) maketh rich, and he addeth no ſorrow with it.</hi> Whereby it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that Induſtry not accompanied with Providence,
<note place="margin">Pro. 16.27</note> is but <hi>Digging up of Evil.</hi> Wiſdom's advice then is (if any dependance) to fix and attribute it on, and to him, who of a Shepherd,
<note place="margin">1 Samuel.</note> and the youngeſt Son of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> raiſed <hi>David</hi> to a Throne; who thankfully acknowledg'd it, and thereby hath left a pattern of gratitude to be imitated by all who have a true ſenſe of their own inabilities and weakneſs.</p>
               <p>It was the plot of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Religion, to preſerve himſelf honeſt, that he might remain Fortunate: Therefore the firſt profitable thing I adviſe my <hi>Citizen</hi> to put in practice, is to be conſtantly and ſincerely Religious; ſo he may expect the fruitful influences of him he puts his truſt in.</p>
               <p>If a man ſhould at every weeks end conſider how he hath ſpent it; how many hours might he reckon up, to have been laviſh'd and idly thrown away,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:32480:46"/>beſides eating and drinking? How many needleſs <hi>Items</hi> would he finde given to ſleep? <hi>Item,</hi> ſeven nights: <hi>Item,</hi> ſo many many afternoons, beſides half hours and quarters at accuſtomed times. Had thoſe men, whoſe Wealth hath made them admired, kept <hi>eight-a-clock-hours,</hi> Fame had never had them on Record: as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>Slug-abeds,</hi> are ſeldome mentioned but with diſparagement. <hi>The Soul of the Sluggard</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) deſireth,
<note place="margin">Pro. 13.4.</note> and hath nothing; but the Soul of the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent man maketh fat.
<note place="margin">Pro. 22.29</note> Seeſt thou a man diligent in his buſineſs</hi> (ſaith the ſame) <hi>he ſhall ſtand before Kings. Adam</hi> in the ſtate of Innocency muſt dreſs the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; and after it was denounced againſt him, <hi>In the ſweat of thy Brows ſhalt thou eat thy Bread.</hi> So the indiſputable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept is <hi>Labour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Labour not</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>for the meat which periſheth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 6.27</note> but for <hi>that which indureth everlaſtingly.</hi> Should we hear onely of <hi>Labour,</hi> and not of <hi>Everlaſting life,</hi> we ſhould be diſcouraged: ſo ſhould we hear of <hi>Labour,</hi> and not of <hi>Proſit,</hi> we could have little comfort in employment. But ſhall we think <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> hath nimble feet, if <hi>ours</hi> be ſlow?
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:32480:46"/>Shall we eat, and not work? ſhall we think with the <hi>Lillies</hi> (which neither ſpin nor labour) <hi>our cloaths will grow upon us?</hi> No, let him that looks for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, take the pains. <hi>Selymus</hi> the firſt, Emperour of the <hi>Turks,</hi> thought Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries unfiniſh'd, if gotten in the Maſters abſence. Juſt as in Military, ſo it is in Civil affairs; and that man may bluſh for ſhame, who puts off his buſineſs to his ſervants, doing nothing himſelf, ſave by thoughts and verbal directions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Julian</hi> the Emperour was aſhamed any man ſhould ſee him ſpit or ſweat; becauſe he thought continual labour ſhould have concocted and dryed up all ſuch ſuperfluities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> of his own accord exempting an Ancient man of ninety years from ſervice, the man having been accuſtomed to exerciſe and labour, and was very luſty at that time; ſuppoſing it a kinde of diſgrace to be deem'd feeble, and fearing <hi>ſloth</hi> would ſhorten his days, he counterfetied himſelf ſick; and keeping his bed, his friends never left lamenting over their fained drooping kinſman, till <hi>Caeſar</hi> to ſatisfie their importunities, and to hearten the old man, cauſed him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to be inrolled one of his Souldiers.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:32480:47"/>Thus ſee how Heathens deteſted <hi>Idleneſs;</hi> and ſhall we, whom Chriſtianity obliges to be diligent and watchful, ſit ſtill? <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cicero) is a burden that man undergoeth with pleaſure. As brightneſs</hi> (ſays <hi>Thales) is to ruſtineſs, ſo excrciſe excelleth idleneſs.
<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.18</note> By much ſlothfulneſs the building decayeth; and through i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſs of the hands, the houſe droppeth through.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I alledge not this againſt a mans im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying others in his affairs, when their burthen is too heavy for him. But I would have a Maſter <hi>Do,</hi> as well as <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect;</hi> for nothing doth more diminiſh his reſpect, than to let his ſervant be ſole Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of his Trade, while himſelf is but Maſter to a Servant: and in the mean while indulging an idle diſpoſition, he renders himſelf leſs honourable than his Man. He muſt Labour, but ſo forecaſt his buſineſs, as to avoid what is too <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous,</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntimely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the Firſt; Haſt makes a bad ſpeed, and Force gives all things ill. The Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons roar, yet they ſuffer hunger; while the Sheep have a Shepherd to provide for them: a too ſharp intention hinders the wiſe conduct of buſineſs. He that's
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:32480:47"/>haſty ſtumbles, and is ſtaid, <hi>Nolens, Volens.</hi> To hurry, is to be intangled; whence it happens, haſt proves ſlow. An over-ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent way in dealing, is never without many indiſcreet actions and wrongs. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Play, he that games paſſionately, ſpoils his judgment; and the more he troubles himſelf, he loſes. He that walks moderately is always with himſelf, and directeth his Concerns with the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage: Therefore <hi>(ſaid a Wiſe Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhman,) Let's ſtay a while, that we may end the ſooner.</hi> The deliberate is always ready for a new change; his <hi>Fair</hi> and <hi>ſoftly,</hi> goes <hi>quick</hi> and <hi>far. Conſideration</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solon</hi>) is <hi>enemy to all untimely at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts.</hi> Conſideration is the root of all noble things; for by her, we do attain to the end of all our hopes. I would have my <hi>Citizen</hi> diligent, but not paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate. They are wofully miſtaken, who fancy buſineſs can never be performed well, without clamour and noyſe. <hi>The Prudent man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) foreſeeth the evil, and hideth himſelf;
<note place="margin">Pro. 23.3.</note> but the ſimple paſs on, and are puniſh'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the ſecond, or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſeaſonableneſs:</hi> there is a time to eat, a time to drink, to ſleep, and to ſport, as well as labour.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:32480:48"/>
                  <hi>Labour</hi> may be reckoned at Meat, which out of time hurteth, not nouriſhes: What's made to chear mans heart, if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duly taken in, periſheth the body. It was the famous ſaying of <hi>Anacharſis</hi> the <hi>Scythian</hi> Philoſopher; <hi>Rule luſt, Temper the tongue, and Bridle the belly. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus Caeſar</hi>'s manner was to ſit down, when thoſe who dined with him had half done, and to riſe up the firſt. Next, we muſt not by Labour, commit <hi>Sacriledge;</hi> we muſt not intrench on the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and make our Souls Feaſts moveables. <hi>Gods time is meaſur'd out by Inches, ours by Ells:</hi> ſince he hath ſo little allotted him, let us not grudge, and abridge it. Be aſtoniſhed and reformed at the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which have faln ſo heavy on thoſe (in the memory of man) who ſlighted the <hi>Seventh day,</hi> and made no conſcience to act according to their wicked and diabolical opinions. How many have been drowned, ventring to ſwim, when they ſhould be at Church! wherein the ſecular Officers of the Church have been always to blame, for minding no more to ſcour thoſe places, which all Summer long are ſo notorious for the multitudes of Youth, who gather
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:32480:48"/>there, and meet their deaths untimely and deſervedly, for treſpaſſing and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imploying their time, contrary to the <hi>Word,</hi> and Laws of the Land, in the ignorance of their Fathers, Friends and Maſters; nay, which is worſe, thereby bring upon the Church ſcandal of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs and remiſneſs in Diſcipline; who can no more remedy theſe omiſſions of Pariſh-Officers, than hinder that ſome Houſes be not broken up, ſometimes by the negligence of Conſtables. How many have had their Legs broken; nay, have ſunk irrecoverably through Ice, in playing at Foot-ball on the <hi>Sacred day.</hi> How many for travelling, working, and acting unlawful and unholy things, have paſt the edge of Gods remarquable ſword of vengeance! Wherefore my <hi>Citizen,</hi> if he intends to eſcape the Title, (which hath damnation at the end of it, if it provokes not the immediate and exemplary juſtice of the Almighty, and the aſſured, though ſlow puniſhment of a <hi>Sabbath-breaker,</hi>) he muſt bend his carnal and ſinful inclinations, and make them obey the voice of the Lord his God, <hi>In keeping holy the ſacred day of reſt.</hi> To fix the more reverence of a Deity
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:32480:49"/>in him, behold here ſome memorable and moſt dreadful Examples on ſuch whom the Ancients abhor'd for their ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religion; for none will tread in ſuch paths, who have any fear of a God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes; as <hi>Socrates</hi> (though a Heathen) after an unintermitted twenty four hours ſtudy, concluded there was and is an <hi>Only Almighty one.</hi> Undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly Satan without his permiſſion could not have declar'd himſelf (by the means of Oracles) ſo wonderfully to the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Heathens; and a Divine right, though Helliſh, hath ſhew'd it ſelf mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellouſly and direfully, to the incroachers thereon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Xerxes</hi> that potent King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> ſent four thouſand men to deſtroy <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Temple at <hi>Delphos,</hi> who were intirely blotted out with rain, lightning and thunder. <hi>Brennus</hi> Captain of a Hoſt of ſupernumerous and barbarous <hi>Gauls,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to deſpoil the ſame Temple: But his Army being diſperſed, more through a hidden terrour that poſſeſt them, than any viſible force, he with a dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ended his own life. There is greater reaſon to look for Judgments to light on our contempt and obſtinacy
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:32480:49"/>in robbing God of the glory we ſhould pay him in his Church (being created for the ſame purpoſe, and it being the leaſt we ought or can do,) than the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients had, for committing ſacriledge in robbing their Temples of their riches, and deſtroying them. Beſides (if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend any thing on Providence) how dare we to wait for Gods bleſſing on <hi>our day,</hi> if we neglect to ſerve him <hi>on his'n?</hi> Nay, if we would proſper on <hi>week-days,</hi> let us pray on them. He, and none but he, who conſecrates the Prime of the morning, may ſtedfaſtly hope increaſe and fruits of his induſtry. The <hi>Jews</hi> being returned from Captivity, were wont <hi>to ſpend one fourth o'th' day in reading the Law,
<note place="margin">Neh. 9.</note> and another fourth part in confeſſing their ſins and in prayer;</hi> And ſhall not we, whoſe mercies are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely beyond theirs, ſhew our ſelves thankful, for having been freed from the ſlavery of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Ignorance and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, from the ravenous jaws of a Needy, Mercenary, Factious, Rebellious, and Bloody rabble of Incendiaries, who, had not he been gracious in the <hi>Reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of King and Church, would by this time have rooted us up, and redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:32480:50"/>us to a condition pitiful, impotent, and fit to be made tributary to the next Invader; from the Raging and diſmal gripes of a Peſtilence, an utter deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Fire; and laſtly, from a ruine (had we our deſerts) which our <hi>Sea-E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies</hi> had inevitably brought on us, had not the Almighty's Mercy ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and his Juſtice? ſhall not we, I ſay, <hi>for all theſe beneſits receiv'd at his hands,</hi> ſpare one hour (and that ſcanty of imployment) in which we ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs a ſenſe of his <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and our <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitableneſs?</hi> We might with ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon plead for a reſpite, if with continual prayer, <hi>our knees,</hi> like thoſe of <hi>Jacobus Minor,</hi> the Son of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> our <hi>Saviours</hi> brother, <hi>were become</hi> (with kneeling) <hi>hard as a Camels hoof.</hi> But our won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſs in it is ſo ſlender, as moſt ſeem to be readier (and would ſooner imbrace it) to wear out their ſtockings in drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Healths, than in <hi>Devotion.</hi> The <hi>Publick</hi> (and in many places <hi>daily) Prayers</hi> of our Church ſhould towards men upright and really Pious, have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurement enough (beſides their obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) to inflame any ones coldneſs and to ſtir up the moſt drowzy and worldly
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:32480:50"/>to ſeek aſſiſtance from a <hi>Power</hi> of ſuch <hi>immenſity</hi> and <hi>grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O times, O manners!</hi> What a Change is here? In King <hi>Edward</hi>'s time, when our Land was newly clear'd from that fog of <hi>Egypt, Romiſh Blindneſs;</hi> with what joy, readineſs, and thankſgiving did the people come to hear the <hi>Liturgy</hi> in their own tongue? But nothing is ſo great and admirable in the beginning, whoſe worth and wonder is not leſſened by little and little. Now men come to it (nay on Sundays) as if <hi>Preaching</hi> were againſt <hi>Prayers,</hi> and by <hi>their conſent,</hi> we ſhould have more Pillars than Proſelytes. It is well, that it it's ſaid,
<note place="margin">Mat. 18.20</note> 
                  <hi>Where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midſt of them.</hi> Had the Promiſe been tyed to a greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, thoſe <hi>few</hi> which meet in ſome Places might doubt of ſucceſs. No que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but our Times might flouriſh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually with former, if our Temples were filled with Praying <hi>unanimouſly</hi> with one <hi>minde</hi> and <hi>ſoul,</hi> as they have been. O the tranſcendent ſweetneſs of <hi>Lita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> (which are uſed in alluſion to the 2 &amp; 17 of <hi>Joel, Let the Prieſts and the Miniſters of the Lord weep before the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:32480:51"/>Porch and the Altar, and let them ſay, Spare thy People)</hi> where many <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>hearts</hi> are lifted up; <hi>hands</hi> in <hi>purity, hearts</hi> in <hi>Piety; hands</hi> in <hi>good Works, hearts</hi> in <hi>good thoughts.</hi> Who is able to conceive the unſpeakable <hi>value</hi> of <hi>Publick Services?</hi> of theſe <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Heavenly Evaporations?</hi> they are more than the <hi>breath</hi> of <hi>Spices;</hi> they are none other than <hi>Emiſſions</hi> of <hi>Paradiſe?</hi> When the <hi>Organs</hi> (uſed in his Majeſties Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and in moſt Colledges and Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drals of his Dominions) are blown; When the <hi>Voices</hi> are heard, and the whole <hi>Quire</hi> of Religious men do ſill the Air with loud cries and <hi>vocal Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonies</hi> of <hi>devout</hi> and <hi>pathetical invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations;</hi> Then do the <hi>Spices</hi> flow, the <hi>Odours</hi> are burnt, and the ſmoke of our <hi>Incenſe</hi> goes up before the Lord, from the Angels hand. To labour when our <hi>Prayers</hi> might <hi>aſcend,</hi> and have the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier <hi>admittance,</hi> ſuch a time is prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous.</p>
               <p>Thus my <hi>Citizen</hi> conſidering what's paſt, and ſquaring his Actions by the foregoing Rules, will finde profit on't, and undiſturbedly fill his bags. <hi>The way of the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) is ſtrength
<note place="margin">Pro. 10.20</note>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:32480:51"/>to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright; but deſtruction ſhall be to the workers of iniquity.</hi> After theſe inſtances, can you imagine, that <hi>ſcantling</hi> of time <hi>Morning-Prayer</hi> takes up, to <hi>leſſen</hi> your gain, and <hi>thwart</hi> your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours? when to <hi>lie abed</hi> till <hi>nine</hi> or <hi>ten</hi> a clock, or to ſpend <hi>four</hi> or <hi>five</hi> hours in a <hi>Mornings draught,</hi> is pocketed up contentedly, and counted no retard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to your buſineſs? If my <hi>Citizen</hi> be guilty of this <hi>Sloth,</hi> and <hi>Companionſhip,</hi> he errs extreamly, and utterly, nay, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly diſowns any neceſſity of returning thanks to him he is indebted to for all he's worth. He is far from conſenting with <hi>David,</hi> when he ſings,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.3.</note> 
                  <hi>My voice ſhalt thou hear in the morning, O Lord, in the morning will I direct my prayer unto thee, and look up.</hi> He is very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, for his <hi>health, preſervation</hi> and <hi>proſperity,</hi> and manifeſts too preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly to carry in his hand an <hi>exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption</hi> from all manner of Miſery. As <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius Tullius</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> boaſted, that the <hi>Goddeſs Fortune</hi> lay with him every night; and therefore was in ſubjection to him. Our <hi>Citizen</hi> (if as aforeſaid inclin'd) does intimate by his Actions, <hi>Providence</hi> to have no more power over
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:32480:52"/>him, than <hi>Fortune</hi> had over <hi>Tullius;</hi> but if he is more inwardly touch'd, he will concur with <hi>David,</hi> by performing what the Royal Prophet teſtifies of himſelf; <hi>But I will ſing of thy power;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.16</note> I will ſing of thy mercy in the morning: for thou haſt been my defence and refuge in the day of my trouble.</hi> He may by ſuch an <hi>unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſubmiſſive,</hi> and <hi>conſtant exerciſe,</hi> aſſume the confidence and <hi>aſſured hope</hi> of the <hi>Man after Gods own heart,</hi> when he ſaid,
<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſal. 30.6.</note> 
                  <hi>And in my proſperity I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be moved.</hi> To keep to my Method, and to quicken your zeal, obſerve what Antiquity relates of our Forefathers De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> gives the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of <hi>moſt Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Godly Prince</hi> to <hi>Arcadius</hi> Emperour of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> who was for his <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Sobriety</hi> highly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd of his Subjects. <hi>God</hi> (ſaith a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Hiſtorian) made <hi>Narſetes</hi> (Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral under the Emperour <hi>Juſtinian</hi>) victorious by Sea and Land, more for his <hi>zealous prayers,</hi> than Force and Valour; Who never <hi>began Fight, went to Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, or mounted on Horsback, before he went to the Temple and ſerved God. Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> the ſecond of that name, and a moſt <hi>holy, vertuous,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:32480:52"/>juſt,</hi> and <hi>merciful Prince,</hi> being driven to a <hi>bleſſed neceſſity;</hi> as he walked in the midſt of his Palace, he ſaw at his feet a <hi>Marble-ſtone,</hi> which was in the form of a <hi>Croſs;</hi> and becauſe he thought it not <hi>Religious</hi> to <hi>ſpurn</hi> it with his feet, he cauſed it to be taken up; under which was found <hi>another,</hi> and ſo a <hi>third</hi> of the ſame ſhape: which laſt, when removed, had hid under it <hi>two Millions of Duckets;</hi> for which he praiſed the bounty of his God. This <hi>laſt</hi> hath effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy and encouragement in abundance to enliven the lumpiſhneſs of any, who hath not abjur'd Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>It's related of the <hi>birds</hi> of <hi>Norway,</hi> that they fly faſter than the fowls of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Country: By an inſtinct of Nature they know the days in that Climate to be very ſhort, as not above three hours long; and therefore they wing it the ſpeedier. My <hi>Citizen</hi> muſt learn of theſe Birds the ſhortneſs of his life, and to be the more induſtrious. He muſt apply all diligence and aſſiduity in the purſuit of Wealth;
<note place="margin">Pro. 9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Whatſoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with all thy might; for there is no work, nor device, nor wiſdome, nor knowledge in the Grave, whither thou
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:32480:53"/>goeſt.
<note place="margin">Pro. 12.24</note> The hand of the Diligent</hi> (ſaith the ſame) <hi>ſhall bear rule; but the ſlothful ſhall be under tribute.</hi> The <hi>Monyed</hi> man is the <hi>Mighty man. Honour, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Royalty</hi> attend on <hi>Riches; Logick</hi> faileth, and <hi>Rhetorick</hi> fainteth, when <hi>Gold</hi> pleads the Cauſe. <hi>Orpheus</hi> his Harp, <hi>Amphion</hi>'s Muſick, <hi>Virgil</hi>'s Muſe, and <hi>Tully</hi>'s Tongue, are ſilent; yea, Thundring <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> will complain of the Squinzy, if Money forbid him to play the Oratour. They onely deſpiſe Riches, which deſpair of them: Like the Fox in the Fable, <hi>curſing the grapes he could not reach.</hi> Nevertheleſs <hi>Riches</hi> are not the chiefeſt good; and therefore wicked men enjoy them. But as they are not Evil in themſelves, it may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a good man to labour for them. <hi>The Poor and Rich meet together</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) and the Lord is the maker of them both.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 22.2.</note> The Holy Ghoſt hath plac'd poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> in the boſome of Rich <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> to ſhew that Rich and Poor, if they be indeniz'd the Kingdome of Grace, have an equal intereſt in that of Glory.</p>
               <p>Secondly, If outward bleſſings might be monopoliz'd to the wicked, the godly
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:32480:53"/>being encompaſſed with fleſh and blood, would think baſely of Religion, of the Worſhip and Service of God; <hi>Therefore endeavour to obtain them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Riches are expedient, for illuſtrating the vertues of Charity, Almſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, and the like: <hi>they are a good by which thou maiſt do good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Men are not ſo apt to take exact notice of thoſe ſpiritual bleſſings wherewith the <hi>Elect</hi> are inwardly ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (ſo God loſes ſome of his glory) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Temporal bleſſings be added to them; <hi>therefore labour for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, Let the conſideration of that great <hi>Senator,</hi> the <hi>Lord Mayor's</hi> Dignity, with his <hi>Brethren,</hi> the <hi>Right Worſhipful Court of Aldermen,</hi> ſhew what in time a man may come to, if he tends his Affairs with that <hi>foreſight, Prudence, Diligence,</hi> and inceſſant <hi>care,</hi> which are able to rank him among the <hi>truly Rich;</hi> and at length, to <hi>advance</hi> him to the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of that <hi>honour</hi> a <hi>Citizen</hi> ought to enable himſelf for, both in <hi>Minde</hi> and <hi>Purſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:32480:54"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Senators ought to be Rich, for theſe</hi> REASONS.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, It is a Pledge of their care of the Commonwealth: it is likely he that hath done well for himſelf, is the better inſtructed how to advance the Publick good, if put to it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Wealth being gotten, they may the more intentively regard Publick Affairs, having enough to maintain Servants for performance of Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in Ruling there muſt be Power and Command: for if a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour be needy, it is to be feared, leſt ſad experience proves the old Proverb to be too true; <hi>That a poor Magiſtrate is a great plague;</hi> and that <hi>weakneſs</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puiſſance</hi> begets contempt to the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance of <hi>juſtice. The Rich ruleth over the Poor</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi>)
<note place="margin">Pro. 27.2.</note> Wherefore let the Honour any man may be called to move him to get Riches. It belonget<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to a Governour (ſaith a great Polititian) to be learned (my Citizen may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:32480:54"/>it in the words <hi>Well Read</hi>) the better to know himſelf, and what he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert Fabian</hi> was Sheriff in the 9 of <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. and was Knighted by him, for his Merits; but is famous eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for a Chronicle he made to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the City. Wiſe to deſigne how to perform, and <hi>Diſcreet</hi> to watch and lay hold on opportunity.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>John Allen</hi> Mereer, and Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> in the 27 of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. was ſworn of the Privy Council to him; being indeed a man Eminent for his Wiſdome and Charity, <hi>Reſolute</hi> in the action of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> without fear or corruption; but above all, to excel o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as much in <hi>Vertue</hi> as <hi>Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matthew Philips</hi> Goldſmith, was Mayor in the 3 year of <hi>Edward</hi> the 4. and was by the ſaid King, for his faithful Service, and Adminiſtration of Juſtice, made Knight of the <hi>Bath. When the Righteous are in Authority the people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce;
<note place="margin">Pro. 29.2.</note> but when the Wicked beareth rule, the people mourn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1190. <hi>Henry Fitz-Allen</hi> Goldſmith, was made the firſt Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> and held it twenty four years together.</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:32480:55"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1380. In the raign of King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, <hi>William Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> Lord Mayor, for his courage in cutting off the Head of <hi>Watt Tyler,</hi> who in a tumultuous manner had rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, and pitched his Camp in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> with his Rout of Raſcals, defying Allegiance, and braving Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty to the teeth; the ſaid <hi>William</hi> for his Valour in beheading the ſaid <hi>Tyler,</hi> in the ſight of his Rabble, was Knighted.</p>
               <p>But excellent Policy hath now ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered it, that every year ſhall have a new Mayor. <hi>Let the chiefeſt Magiſtrates</hi> (ſaith a famous Machiavilian) <hi>be perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual; the leſſer yearly, ſtill removing.</hi> And the <hi>Turks</hi> own this Maxim, as uſeful in many of their Governments.</p>
               <p>Beſides other Reaſons, this is none of the leaſt: It encourageth every man to take pains, when his Merits may be ſo Crowned. But Ambition muſt be avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. There is a two-fold way to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; Direct, when God calls; Indirect, when Man ſeeks it without his Warrant My <hi>Citizen</hi> muſt minde the way, and not meerly the end. Let him not run Honours, but expect them; not as one
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:32480:55"/>that hunts after, but deſerves them. <hi>The conditions of Honour are ſuch</hi> (ſaith a Wiſe man) <hi>that ſhe enquireth for him ſhe never ſaw, runneth after him that flies from her, honours him that eſteems her not, gives to him requires not, and truſteth him ſhe knoweth not. He that followeth after righteouſneſs, findeth life,
<note place="margin">Pro. 21.21</note> righteouſneſs and honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The World at preſent differs much from <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great's humour, who commanded both <hi>Grecians</hi> and <hi>Barbarians</hi> ſhould no more be diſguiſed by their garments; but that all vertuous and men of fortitude ſhould be counted <hi>Grecians;</hi> and all vicious, and ill addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, <hi>Barbarians.</hi> Quite contrary now, a man bears not the mark of his deſert about him. Vertuous men are not now ſo honoured, that they may be <hi>Triumphs</hi> imprint their actions deeply in mens Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories; nor is there ſuch an equalneſs in States, that all mens actions ſhould be ſeen with the ſame judgment: and indeed 'twere pity it ſhould be ſo now; for Pride would ruine all in a moment. <hi>Marcellus</hi> the <hi>Romane</hi> dedicated two Temples; one to <hi>Vertue,</hi> the other to <hi>Honour;</hi> and contrived them in ſuch
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:32480:56"/>manner, that none could enter into that of <hi>Honour,</hi> ſave through that of <hi>Vertue.</hi> My <hi>Citizen</hi> if he would be honoured, muſt be vertuouſly Rich. It was worthily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by <hi>Maximilian</hi> the <hi>German</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, to one who deſired his Letters-Patents to ennoble him: <hi>I am able</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>to make thee rich, but Vertue muſt make thee Noble.</hi> Having cleared my Point concerning the neceſſity of ſtriving to be Rich, I now proceed.</p>
               <p>As I would have my <hi>Citizen</hi> labour, I mean it not inceſſantly: there is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between providing for himſelf and family, and doing nothing elſe. The buſineſs of his <hi>Soul,</hi> and the refreſhing of his <hi>Body,</hi> muſt be look'd into; beſides the intereſt the <hi>Publick</hi> hath in his time.</p>
               <p>The labours of leſs than the Worlds third part maintain the whole. How many then live <hi>Idly?</hi> Almoſt all Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which are half the number; or if Women be imployed in their ſtead, Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> throw away their time. Put to, all that are inclos'd in the pale of Gentility and Eſtate; and laſtly, adde the great number of Beggers, and you will compute <hi>few</hi> Labourers; and of thoſe, <hi>few</hi> well im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imploy'd.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:32480:56"/>If then leſs than the Worlds third part maintains the whole, leſs than the third part of my <hi>Citizens</hi> time one day with another will ſuffice for him; unleſs his <hi>Private</hi> concerns be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, and he be forc'd to attend <hi>Publick</hi> ones.</p>
               <p>But before I treat of his induſtrious gettings, let me touch a little on his ſpendings. Firſt, I would have him think it more honourable to ſtoop to petty ſavings, than to baſe gain. Luſty ſpenders, and dainty feeders, ſo they have it, care not by what means. He muſt not cloſe and practically adhere to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligula,</hi> that profuſe Emperours opinion, who profeſſed all kinde of thrift to be durtineſs of Nature. <hi>It is better</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bias,</hi> one of the ſeven Sages) <hi>to be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for having much, than to be pitied for ſpending all.</hi> Let him imitate <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> that frugal King of <hi>France,</hi> who thought it no diſcredit to tye a knot in a broken point, and wear it again.</p>
               <p>Secondly, He muſt not haunt <hi>Taverns</hi> too much; which is the Epidemical fault of the <hi>City.</hi> I know it is not company, but the want of diſcretion in the choice and uſe of it, that overthrows a man:
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:32480:57"/>beſides <hi>needleſs expences,</hi> how can that man be fit for buſineſs, who makes his body a continual quagmire? <hi>Wine</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) is a mocker,
<note place="margin">Pro. 20.1.</note> ſtrong drink is raging; and whoſoever is deceived there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is not wiſe.</hi> In another place: <hi>Who hath woe?
<note place="margin">Pro. 23.29, 30.</note> who hath ſorrow? who hath contentions? who hath bablings? who hath wounds? who hath redneſs of eyes? They that tarry long at wine.</hi> In ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hear and obey.
<note place="margin">Pro. 23.31, 32, 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Look not upon wine when it is red, when it giveth its colour; At laſt it biteth like a Serpent, and ſtingeth like an Adder: Thine eyes ſhall behold ſtrange women, and thy heart ſhall utter perverſe things.</hi> Now if thou pretendeſt to reaſon, which diſtinguiſhes thee from a Beaſt, hearken to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients, how they reprove drunkenneſs and exceſs. <hi>Wine</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempereth the wit, weakneth the feet, and overpowreth the vital ſpirits. Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs</hi> (ſaith <hi>Plato) and intemperance, is a root proper to every diſeaſe. Origen</hi> (one of the Primitive Fathers) ſaith, <hi>it makes a man a Beaſt, a ſtrong man weak, a wiſe man a fool.</hi> One <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthenes</hi> a Heathen, hapning to be at one of <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Feaſts, and often urged
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:32480:57"/>to drink as others did, anſwered, <hi>he would not; for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>who drinketh to</hi> Alexander, <hi>had need of a Phyſician.</hi> Laſtly, behold ſome ſad conſequences of taking in liquor too freely, and then be exceſſive if thou dareſt. <hi>Aruntius</hi> a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane,</hi> being drunk deflowred his own Daughter <hi>Medullina;</hi> for which ſhe immediately kill'd him. <hi>Alexander</hi> that mighty Conquerour, in his drink often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times committed ſuch tragical deeds, as engaged ſome of his Servants to plot the ſhortning of his days by poyſon, leſt he ſhould, if he lived longer, in his raging fits deſtroy them all. Nevertheleſs <hi>if thou canſt not abſtain fellowſhip, then drink as in the Primitive times, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding God is to be remembred both in Night and Day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Next, what ſhall I ſay of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous Diet. <hi>The belly</hi> (ſaith <hi>Crates</hi> the Philoſopher) <hi>is an unthankful beaſt, never requiting the pleaſure done, but craveth continually more than it needeth.</hi> I'me ſure he that ſaid, <hi>In my Country the belly is the God,</hi> if now living, his words would be found too true. What infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite ſums of money are ſacrificed to it, in procuring the Earth, the Air, and the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:32480:58"/>Sea, to centre at one Table, making Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-Cloths like St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s ſheet, including creatures clean and unclean? How many are there to be found that imitate <hi>Muleaſſes</hi> King of <hi>Tunis,</hi> who ſpent a hundred Crowns on the dreſſing of a Peacock? Certainly many of our <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Gluttons</hi> ſhew too well by their Acates and coſtly dainties, that their wills and inclinations are not far behind hiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. We are ſick of thoſe things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we live. The moſt wholſome food, the leaſt Cookery: Diſeaſes ſpring from corruptions and riotous eating. What profit either to Body, Purſe or Soul can it be; nay, what pleaſure, with <hi>Geta</hi> the <hi>Romane</hi> Emperous, to ſwill and cram for three days and nights together? If your power could bring together, like <hi>Sergius Galba,</hi> that monſtrous Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, ſeven thouſand Fowls at one Meal, in twenty four hours; how much luſtier, healthfuller, and briſker would you be, than he who hath dined or ſupped on one poor ſingle Diſh? My <hi>Citizen</hi> is much miſtaken, if he holds that moſt ſtrength is drawn out of the daintieſt and moſt luxurious fare. <hi>Socrates</hi> our worthy Tutor, inviting once certain of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:32480:58"/>his Friends to a Feaſt, was reproved for his ſlender proviſion. <hi>If they be vertuous</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it is enough;</hi> if not, <hi>there is too much.</hi> If our Forefathers were alive now, they could hardly tell the names of our needleſs variety of Diſhes, without the help of a <hi>Kitching-Dictionary.</hi> They would wonder Art ſhould keep School in the Kitching, and that our Palats ſhould be ſo ingenious. The Ancients have in their words and deeds ſcourged this vice to the purpoſe; and if my <hi>Citizen</hi> means to attain any thing above the reach of his mouth, he muſt ſet himſelf to trace the ſteps of thoſe, <hi>Hiſtory</hi> makes famous for their <hi>abſtinence.</hi> King <hi>Cyrus,</hi> being aſked by <hi>Artabanus</hi> (when he lay once in the Camp) what he would have for Supper? <hi>Bread,</hi> anſwered he; <hi>for I hope we ſhall finde ſome Fountain to furniſh us with Drink.</hi> Therefore let my <hi>Citizen</hi> learn to be temperate. <hi>Gorgias</hi> the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, being demanded how he arrived to the number of a hundred and eight years, anſwered; <hi>By never eating or drinking any thing for pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finally, if nothing but the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of danger, can prevail with him to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:32480:59"/>abſtain; it can't chuſe but afright, and make his blood recoil, to know, that <hi>Septimus Severus,</hi> and <hi>Jovianus,</hi> two Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Emperours, in their height of Cups and Plates, ſurrendred their lives. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eydes</hi> a Philoſopher, through exceſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired ignominiouſly. <hi>Valentinianus</hi> an Emperour ſuddenly dyed of a Surfeit. Pardon me for telling him flat and plain, though a little immethodically; if his tendency to ſuch exorbitances be not bounded, though his days partly through a ſtrong conſtitution may be prolonged, (and that happens but ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the Experimenters) yet I dare be ſo bold as to ſtick on him the true and woful jeſt of <hi>Diogenes,</hi> who hearing the Houſe of a Prodigal was to be ſold; <hi>I knew</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>very well, that a houſe ſo full of meat and drink, would vomit out its Maſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Needleſs Expences in Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel muſt be examined. <hi>He that waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his wealth to follow every faſhion</hi> (ſaith one of our already quoted Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,) <hi>and hateth his ſubſtance to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his bravery, may be counted the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers friend, the Taylors fool, and his Own foe.</hi> One bragging of his Golden Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:32480:59"/>was thus anſwered; <hi>The praiſe is due to the metal, not the man.</hi> That is the moſt ornamental, which makes the more vertuous. <hi>I am not ſumptuous</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seneca) yet no man can live otherwiſe at</hi> Rome. <hi>Why do we deceive our ſelves?</hi> (goes he on) <hi>the Evil is within us; it cleaves to our bowels; the fault is our own. Diogenes,</hi> (whom we newly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) going from <hi>Sparta</hi> to <hi>Athens,</hi> was aſked by the way, whence he came, and whither he went; who anſwered, <hi>He came from Men, and was going to Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men:</hi> noting the <hi>Effeminacy</hi> of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians,</hi> who for their delicacy and niceneſs in Food and Rayment, were derided by all <hi>Grecia.</hi> St. <hi>Bernard</hi> preaching the Funeral-Sermon of his own Steward, among other his commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons gave him this; That He was great even in ſmall matters, his care and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection extending to the moſt tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial and ſlighteſt things. Let my <hi>Citizen</hi> imitate him. Happy is he that deſerves the Title, <hi>Faithful in a little;</hi> he ſhall be made owner of a great deal. Let the Example of <hi>Ageſilaus,</hi> King of <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> moderate my <hi>Citizens</hi> airiſhneſs and apiſhneſs, who was wont to wear
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:32480:60"/>one Sute both Winter and Summer. Let it moderate I ſay, ſeeing there are within <hi>London</hi> not a few <hi>Tradeſmen,</hi> whoſe beſt parts lie in the frequent change of <hi>Suits,</hi> as if the ſnake was to be loved for its bright ſkin; they ſtrutting like an Actor, whoſe Rich habits being laid aſide, and his Part done. He is rare to be met withal, that can ſhew himſelf extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary out of his Theatre, wherein my Shopkeeper in many places equals him, as appearing dull and inſipid in all things, ſave in cloaths, lying, and ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> was not aſham'd to wear what was wrought by his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: and is it mean and durty to trace a man ſo famous? But our <hi>City,</hi> you'l ſay, is much exalted, ſince a hundred years. Remember, or (if you ne'r read ſo much) read now, that Romes <hi>pride and idleneſs was</hi> Romes <hi>ruine. Citizens Wives and Daughters</hi> now ſcorn to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in Kitchin-affairs; the beſt quality of a good and a true <hi>Houſwife.</hi> They had rather make a pattern of <hi>C. Marius</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> Kinſwoman, who being great with childe, yet at a Solemnity coveting to appear ſlender-waſted, laced
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:32480:60"/>her ſelf ſo ſtraight, as ſhe immediately fell into travail, miſcarried, and died. Our Town Wives and Maids <hi>(their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents muſt take ſome of the blame and ſhame)</hi> hold it more becoming to pinion up themſelves in a narrow Bodiſs, that they may gain the praiſe of having a handſome body, than to adorn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as it's convenient for perſons of any buſineſs. Where we may obſerve what conſiderable diſadvantages, nay, downright loſſes, proceed from this very neglect of Parents, and Idleneſs (in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of <hi>City-breeding</hi> as it ought to be) in their Daughters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> the Parents omit their Duty to God in Training up their Children as they might never depart from it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> they loſe by not exerciſing their Children in ſuch things, as they might manage to their Credit and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in their Parents abſence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> they get ſuch a cuſtome of fluttiſhneſs and improvidence, as makes them uncapable of improving to the beſt advantage what they are concern'd to perform, either as <hi>maids</hi> or <hi>married.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> if married, they are eager in purſuit of ſome Recreations they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:32480:61"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:32480:61"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:32480:62"/>when ſingle, <hi>through their Friends weakneſs;</hi> therein oftentimes throwing off all obedience to their <hi>Husbands;</hi> all ſenſe of the want &amp; loſs a <hi>Wife</hi> puts a man to, when ever and anon ſhe is pleas'd to freak it; all concernment for a Family; and, which is worſt of all, occaſion by their ſlips thoſe grounds of Scandal that reflect ſo ſharply on the whole City, for ſuffring their <hi>Chucks</hi> ſo groſly to abuſe them. If they were bred anſwerable to a <hi>Tradeſmans</hi> Daughter, though never ſo reſponſible, every <hi>Citizen</hi> ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the rule of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> perſon of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, who hardly acquainted his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with the difference between <hi>Courſe</hi> and <hi>Fine</hi> before they were marriagable, and then he ſet them out gorgeouſly, and to admiration; nay, with no loſs to his Purſe; for their <hi>thriſtineſs</hi> had hoarded up for thoſe days; their lowly educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to <hi>loſtineſs</hi> of ſpirit, <hi>eaſe</hi> and <hi>ignorance,</hi> added to their luſtre, when they came to ſhine among ſo many <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, flitting, goſſipping, idle, proud</hi> and <hi>careleſs Females,</hi> as then appeared in the World. In ſhort, my <hi>Citizen</hi> muſt ſave any thing he can, without <hi>loſs to his credit and hurt to his conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:32480:62"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> I had almoſt quite ſkipt or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got a <hi>devouring practice,</hi> call'd <hi>Gaming;</hi> a poyſon gilded o'er, pleaſant to look upon, but dangerous to take; beſides, the gain by it is diſhoneſt. <hi>Cards</hi> and <hi>Dice</hi> are ſmooth, deceitful, and thieviſh ſlights, unbecoming the cloſeneſs of a <hi>Citizen,</hi> as Maſter of a family, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to the welfare of all his Fortunes. How privily do ſome men bring their whole eſtates to nothing, falling like lightning, ſooner <hi>felt</hi> then <hi>foreſeen,</hi> &amp; all by this unthrifty ſport. Certainly <hi>Aurelius Alexander</hi> Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> was not beſides himſelf when he made a Law, <hi>that any one being found at Dice, ſhould be eſteemed frantick, a meer Natural, and as one that wanteth wit and diſcretion to govern himſelf.</hi> If St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s advice was put in ure, <hi>Gaming</hi> would quickly be forſaken, as not worth the pains; who counſel'd, <hi>that all winnings and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage ariſing from Play ſhould be beſtowed on the poor.</hi> If there be any real pleaſure in <hi>Games,</hi> or Sports, it is founded on the glory gotten by exerciſe of the body, by underſtanding what is graceful; as nothing can be more, than to be active, and ſkilful in the moſt civil and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:32480:63"/>appurtenances of a <hi>Citizen.</hi> The <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ate</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> forbad any manner of <hi>playing</hi> for Money, except thoſe of <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering</hi> who was the beſt <hi>Wraſtler,</hi> who threw an <hi>Iron Ball</hi> fartheſt, who caſt a <hi>Dart</hi> beſt, and who <hi>Out-run</hi> or <hi>Leap'd</hi> each other. If my <hi>Citizen</hi> accuſtom'd himſelf to the moſt martial and uſeful exerciſes of his Country, it would raiſe his Repute, preſerve his Health, free him from thinking too much on Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and the Tavern; and by his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple encourage others to return to the <hi>ſimplicity</hi> (if it deſerves the ſtile) of their <hi>Anceſtors.</hi> Never was it known, that any <hi>dyed</hi> for joy of winning anothers Money. But <hi>Diagoras</hi> the <hi>Rhodian,</hi> and <hi>Chilon</hi> the <hi>Greeian,</hi> hearing their <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> had bore away the <hi>Prize</hi> at the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympick Games,</hi> felt in them ſuch a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Spleen,</hi> as they were <hi>ſtifled</hi> with joy. <hi>Croſſing the appetite, as it leads to Vertue, ſo it doth to Profit.</hi> Having thus broken the Ice, I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cunning</hi> is a crooked Wiſdome; let him ſhun that then, and faſten on one more direct, which is not without hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty or ability, and teaches the neceſſity
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:32480:63"/>of knowing the parties well with whom he deals. He muſt dive into their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, humour, inclination, deſignes, and proceedings; ſo the nature of buſineſs in hand muſt be comprehended. A ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficial knowledge is not enough; a man muſt penetrate the inſide, and ſee things in themſelves, with their accidents and conſequents belonging thereto; joyning theſe two together, it will be eaſie for him to gain, if according to the diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of perſons and affairs, he change his ſtyle and manners of proceeding; as a wiſe Sea-man, who according to the divers ſtate of the Sea, and change of the winds, doth diverſly turn his Sails and Rudder: if he ſcans a Cuſtomers temper, he may lead him; knowing his ends, he may perſwade him, and mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his weakneſs he may awe him; if the quality of the buſineſs be underſtood (in the finding whereof every mans own obſervation muſt be ſet a work) if it be diligent 'twill bring forth more than the beſt Writer is able to utter. <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and inſtruction is the beſt way to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His words I would have to be few; for, <hi>He</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>that hath know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:32480:64"/>ſpareth his words, and a man of underſtanding is of an excellent ſpirit. Cleanthes</hi> being deſired by one to teach his Son a ſhort ſentence, anſwered, <hi>Be ſilent.</hi> For beſides the advantage he hath of the talker, in receiving all <hi>gratis,</hi> ſecrecy is ſafer than ſpeech: It is better to have his ſimplicity doubted, than to ſpeak inconveniently, idly, or needleſly. If all men thought alike, <hi>ſilence</hi> were unneceſſary; but ſince the Speaker and Expoſitour utter and receive with different minds, <hi>ſpeech</hi> can't carry her meaning always, juſt as a man would have her; therefore a man muſt defend her impotency by keeping her in, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he may put a Knife in t'other hand to ſtab himſelf. <hi>Whoſo keepeth his mouth and tongue, keepeth his ſoul from trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> The <hi>Italian</hi> Proverb is, <hi>The tongue of a wiſe man is hid in his heart. Iſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> the <hi>Grecian</hi> Oratour, leſt his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars at any time ſhould ſhame him by their words, never admitted any into his School, without a double pay; firſt to learn <hi>ſilence,</hi> and then to <hi>ſpeak,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially what was certain.</p>
               <p>Next, his Servants muſt be enjoyn'd ſecrecy. It is well their Indentures
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:32480:64"/>mention it; but it was better if they more regarded it. The <hi>Moors</hi> are wont to cut off their privities who tell ſecrets. The <hi>Egyptians</hi> uſed to cut out his tongue, that blab'd abroad all he knew, having no power over his unruly inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The <hi>Turks</hi> have <hi>Mutes,</hi> perſons deaf to all lamentation, and dumb to all diſcovery, to perform execution; who ſhould be nearly imitated by my <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> Servants. If <hi>Flavius</hi> had not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed to <hi>Scylla</hi> the moſt unfortified part of <hi>Athens,</hi> he had lain before it labour in vain.</p>
               <p>Again, I would have my <hi>Citizen</hi> wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer than to unfold all his concerns to his wife. Every mans experience tells him of the miſchief occaſioned by womens tongues. In the raign of <hi>Auguſtus Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, Fulvius</hi> having revealed a matter of privacy to his wife, they were both put to death. Far be it from me to have ſo cruel a thought, to believe no woman now alive deſerves <hi>Solomons</hi> praiſe, who ſaith,
<note place="margin">Pro. 31.26</note> 
                  <hi>A vertuous woman openeth her mouth with wiſdome.</hi> Certainly he is highly bleſſed, whoſe <hi>Conſort</hi> may lay claim to this commendation. But as the Pool of <hi>Betheſda</hi> had little vertue, ſave
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:32480:65"/>when the Angel at a certain ſeaſon went down into it, to the abſolute healing of him that ſtept in next: ſo a man may wait a long time before he happens on the opportunity of embracing the comfort, help, and counſel he hopes to enjoy in a <hi>prudent Wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If he does impart his ſecrets, he muſt know, they can't lie hid ſave in a few. There is an infallible Precept; <hi>Lay your Eſtate, if need requires, upon many; your thoughts and weighty intents upon few.</hi> For it is hard to find in a crowd of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidents, one who will not abuſe them to his particular profit. <hi>Tattling</hi> was once a ſafeguard, when the <hi>Geeſe</hi> preſerv'd the <hi>Roman Capitol;</hi> but ſuch examples are rare in Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>For his <hi>ſpeaking,</hi> let me deliver this, He muſt conſult with himſelf. I never knew a man better himſelf by his raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and paſſion. <hi>The perturbations of the minde</hi> (ſaith <hi>Anaxagoras</hi>) <hi>do puniſh reaſon, and blinde the judgment.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my <hi>Citizen</hi> muſt balance the leaſt circumſtances, as he would chuſe to eat what's fitteſt for his bodies health. So anger impairing both body and minde, he ſhould throughly conſider before
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:32480:65"/>he ſpeaks. <hi>Haſtineſs is ever attended by repentance. Wrath and rigour</hi> (ſaith <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſocrates) lead ſhame in a Leaſe.</hi> Beſides, <hi>He that is ſoon angry dealeth fooliſhly.
<note place="margin">Pro. 14.17.</note> He that is ſlow to wrath,
<note place="margin">Pro. 14.29</note> is of great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; but he that is haſty of ſpirit exalteth folly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To proceed: let him that deſires his actions ſhould go forward with a profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſucceſs, deliberate upon them.
<note place="margin">Pro. 15.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Without counſel purpoſes are diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> Wiſe men ſay, <hi>A man muſt conſult ſlowly, and execute ſpeedily, ponder lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely, and accompliſh expeditiouſly.</hi> Yet ſudden in counſel, proves oftentimes proſperous in event; but it is very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. As he muſt adviſe with himſelf, ſo with others (becauſe no mans wiſdom comprehends all buſineſs) <hi>For in the multitude of Counſellers there is ſafety.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 11.14</note> However, he may ask what is beſt to be done, without telling his own reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as depending on them; and take the matter back into his own hands, to evidence to the World, that the final di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection proceeds from himſelf. He muſt notwithſtanding conſider, to whom he breaks his minde. It's an old Precept, <hi>Truſt few:</hi> it's almoſt as old, <hi>Truſt none.</hi>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:32480:66"/>To counſel, is the chiefeſt part of a Friend; but let him be ſo aſſuredly, to whom you diſplay your thoughts. Look eſpecially and exactly, that he be quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with <hi>honeſty</hi> and <hi>ſufficiency. The words of a friend</hi> (ſays a Wiſe man) <hi>joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with true affection, give life to the heart, and comfort a minde oppreſſed with care.</hi> Such a friend reſembles <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion,</hi> who when one of his intimates was deſperately inclin'd to caſt himſelf away, told him he ſhould not; <hi>for he was made his friend to that purpoſe.</hi> For the acting of things duly conſulted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, times and ſeaſons muſt be well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; precipitation is an enemy to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and the ſtep-mother of all actions. Affectatious and formal diſpatches are dangerous; and like what Phyſicians call Pre-digeſtion, or too quick conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which ſurely fills the body full of crudities, and hidden ſeeds of diſeaſes: therefore meaſure not diſpatch by the time of employment, but the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the buſineſs.</p>
               <p>If the caſe requires help of a <hi>Foreman</hi> or <hi>Journeyman,</hi> let him embrace the uſe of his abilities, and vertuous Service; let him uſe him upon extraordinary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:32480:66"/>onely, otherwiſe his own ceaſing in buſineſs may deprave his affections and underſtanding. Let it be alſo upon good terms, thankfully, and reſpectively, principally remembring <hi>the Labourer is worthy of his hire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſome caſes my <hi>Citizen</hi> may mingle profit with honeſty, and compound with both; though he muſt not turn his back to honeſty, yet he may ſometimes go about and coaſt it, with a skill, better practis'd than expreſt; ſomething which may be done openly, muſt be done ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, becauſe of the miſconſtruing World; but this is a good Rule: Avoid and abhor all unjuſt means, but ſearch, ſpy out, and diligently cleave to the moſt juſt, plauſible, and feaſible.</p>
               <p>It's expedient for my <hi>Citizen</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelf with the Buckler of <hi>Diſtruſt,</hi> which is a great ſhare of Prudence; it is the very ſinew of Wiſdom, for my <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen</hi> to take heed of all men: the nature of the world induces him to this, being wholly compos'd of lyes, fraud, and counterfeit dealing. <hi>It's hard</hi> (ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relius) to cozen Diſtruſt with falſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, Conceit ſtanding at the enemies dore.</hi> One <hi>Opimius</hi> lying dangerouſly
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:32480:67"/>ſick of a Lethargy, when ſome would ſhare his goods before the breath was out his body, his careful <hi>Phyſician</hi> caus'd his Money to be poured out before him, and <hi>bid him awake, to live.</hi> So <hi>diſtruſt</hi> will cure a Lethargy, make a ſleepy man wakeful, and arm him againſt poverty; them he truſts he muſt have good expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of, diſguiſing his ſuſpition; for open <hi>diffidence</hi> inviteth as much to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, as an over-careleſs confidence. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dreading cauſleſly, have taught the ſuſpected perſons to beguile indeed; whereas a profeſt aſſurance, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved a deſire to deceive by obliging <hi>Fidelity.</hi> Every man would be credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and a belief of his honeſty doth many times engage him to retain it; wherefore a profeſt truſt agrees well with a conceal'd diffidence. In the practice whereof he muſt be very circumſpect; for I cannot warrant it in all caſes to be lawful.</p>
               <p>From this orderly diſtruſt proceeds a commendable, cloſe, Commodious car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, which in frivolous matters muſt for a mans credit ſake be laid aſide. Thus with applauſe he may deal privily in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of greateſt concern. <hi>Curious ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleties,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:32480:67"/>when once vented, diſſolve to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let him not keep <hi>Inferiours</hi> ſo diſtant, as afterwards to ſtand in need of them. It was the wiſdom of a <hi>French</hi> King, to ſtoop below his dignity, to win that man to him that might benefit or hurt him. Let him be <hi>liberal</hi> in his words, and ſo he beſtows <hi>coſtleſs favours;</hi> Let him be <hi>free</hi> in his deeds; <hi>for one good turn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets another.</hi> It was obſerved, <hi>Sejanus, Tyberius</hi> his favourite, could never have been advanced, without an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of men, on whom he plenteouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd his kindneſs. Yet here my <hi>Citizens</hi> diſcretion muſt guide him; for ſmall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits are ſoon forgotten, and large or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily overcharge: ſome ungrateful ones neglect them, and ſome would have none alive, to whom they are indebted, wiſhing with all their hearts the death of their Benefactour.</p>
               <p>In converſing with <hi>Equals,</hi> let him pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs himſelf to be leſs than they; let him be courteous and affable to them: for they that are ſo, will finde their worſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to be greater Friends than natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Brothers will be to men high-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
<note place="margin">Pro. 29.23</note> 
                  <hi>A mans pride</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon)
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:32480:68"/>ſhall bring him low; but honour ſhall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the humble in ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If he deals with his <hi>Superiours,</hi> let him make all the uſe he can of them, but not truſt in them: among all mortal things, there is none more fading than <hi>that power</hi> which derives not its ſupport from its ſelf; it is common for one man to be unfortunate, through his depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on another. Let him endeavour by good and laudable courſes to acquire the opinion of all honeſt men, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports much to ſhorten the way leading to an eminent eſteem; ſo let him ſtrive in his riſing to be aſſiſted by many, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he will finde himſelf oppreſt with age before he be <hi>Rich</hi> or well <hi>known.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus let him be <hi>diligent</hi> in the queſt of Riches and Credit, but not over-vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and long: he knows not how to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, that is ignorant when he has enough; therefore let him be content with what he may have; for Abundance is not the end, but change of evils. If doing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to preſcription, he miſs <hi>Wealth</hi> and <hi>Eſteem,</hi> let him not ſlip <hi>Vertue;</hi> for though <hi>Fortune</hi> frowns, it's no diſgrace or damage to be <hi>Vertuous.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:32480:68"/>
               <p>Thus my <hi>Citizen</hi> ſhall live in his <hi>Calling.</hi> Firſt, in the <hi>Calling</hi> God hath fitted him with abilities for; and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, if he came to it lawfully, and by the ordinary way of the place he inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits. For any <hi>Calling</hi> otherwiſe attain'd is improper, uſurping, and the perſon ought to be ſoundly fined for his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</p>
               <p>Now I have ſhewed how my <hi>Citizen</hi> ſhall live profitably; but if onely to himſelf, it is too poor an end for an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man: he muſt not be right earth, which ſtands meerly upon its own Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, whereas all things having an <hi>affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> with the Heavens, move upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Centre, and therefore benefit it. <hi>The liberal man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cicero) daily ſeeks out occaſion to put his vertue in practiſe. He that hath a bountiful eye,
<note place="margin">Pro. 22.9.</note> ſhall be bleſſed. Dionyſius</hi> the Elder, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into his Sons Chamber, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding there great ſtore of rich Jewels and Gold, ſaid unto him, <hi>My Son, I did not give thee theſe Riches to uſe in this ſort, but to impart them to thy Friends.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:32480:69"/>
               <head>Of Benefiting Others.</head>
               <p>THe aforeſaid <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſed of one that had hidden great ſtore of Money, commanded him upon pain of death to bring it to him, which he did, ſave ſome which he reſerv'd and bought an Inheritance. Whereof <hi>Dionyſius</hi> hearing, he ſent him back that he took from him, ſaying, <hi>Now thou knoweſt how to uſe riches, I reſtore what I had from thee.</hi> Now that I am about to treat of neceſſary Expences, I ſhall begin firſt with my <hi>Citizens</hi> obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to his <hi>Wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are taught by the light of Nature, that in a Family, the firſt and chiefeſt care ſhould be of the <hi>Wife. Live joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) with the Wife whom thou loveſt,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.9.</note> all the days of the life of thy vanity, which God hath given thee under the Sun; for that is thy portion in this life, and in thy labour which thou takeſt under the Sun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Certainly a <hi>Wife</hi> is a great Officer in a little Commonwealth, the <hi>Houſe;</hi> for
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:32480:69"/>if a <hi>good Wife,</hi> ſhe is grave abroad, wiſe at home, patient to ſuffer, conſtant to love, friendly to her Neighbours, profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to her Houſhold; and rather than ſhe'l be the impediment to a worthy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize, ſhe'l accompany her Huſband, as <hi>Ipſicrates</hi> did <hi>Mithridates</hi> her Royal Lord, like a Page in his Wars. It's un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable, the beſt and moſt meritorious deeds have been acted by ſingle perſons, who have ſought <hi>eternity</hi> in <hi>memory,</hi> not <hi>poſterity;</hi> and in regard of <hi>liberty,</hi> the unmarried man is happieſt. Some have ſaid wittily, and in my opinion devoutly, <hi>Marriage fills the Earth, and Virginity Heaven:</hi> but they ſpeak better, who demanded, how <hi>Heaven ſhould be full, if the Earth were empty.</hi> Without <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage</hi> the Earth would be depopulated. The <hi>Jews</hi> had ſuch a reverence for <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried folks,</hi> as any were exempted from the Wars, or any other Military Office, the firſt year after their <hi>Wedding-day.</hi> The <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> regarded the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling of their Country ſo narrowly, as he who choſe rather to maintain a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs,</hi> than venter into <hi>Wedlock</hi> (thereby ſowing on Sand, and exhauſting that ſpirit profuſely and unprofitably, which
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:32480:70"/>naturally tends to, and produces like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) and lawfully to beget props for his Family and Country, was in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer-time kept cloſe Priſoner, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the recreation every one enjoy'd in their Feſtivals, Sports, Games and Shews; and in the Winter he was in froſty and the coldeſt weather, expoſed (and forc'd to walk round the Market) in his Shirt onely, to do Penance before all whom he indeavour'd to deprave by ſuch a deſtructive Example. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned and ancient <hi>Romans</hi> (much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from the preſent laſcivious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained ones) were wont to fine ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely, any who fancied a ſingle life, not permitting them to execute any honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Office in their <hi>Republick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is commendable for my <hi>Citizen</hi> to Marry; but ſince his negligence may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do his Wife, he muſt ſooner part with his life, loving her ſo dearly, as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the imitation of <hi>Tiberius Gracchus</hi> the <hi>Romane,</hi> who finding two Serpents in his Chamber, inquired of a Southſayer the meaning; Who told him, if he ſlew the <hi>Male,</hi> he ſhould die firſt; if the <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male,</hi> his Wife: but he loving his Wife extreamly, ſlew the <hi>Male,</hi> and ſoon
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:32480:70"/>after paſt out of this world himſelf.</p>
               <p>The ancient Heathens us'd to place <hi>Mercury</hi> by <hi>Venus;</hi> to ſhew what need the affections of <hi>Marriage</hi> have of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Wiſdom to rule and order them. God caſt <hi>Adam</hi> into a ſleep, whilſt he made him a Wife of one of his Ribs: Upon which one moralizeth very quaintly thus; <hi>The Affections ought to ſleep about this work; Reaſon to wake, as in the choice of a Wife, ſo in the gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning her when he has her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When my <hi>Citizen</hi> (if ſingle) is min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to alter or double his condition, let him do his beſt to pick out a perſon of ſhape, and bearing continually about her ſomething lovely, whereby (if he be looſly given) ſhe may reclaim him; if he wavers, ſhe may retain him; but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that her own comelineſs may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, and enlarge the fruit of her womb. For crooked perſons, both alienate their Huſbands affections, and by the narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their wombs, ſpoil what Nature forms therein. Secondly, let him look after a reaſonable Portion; and though one ſaid, <hi>he would have a Dinner, as well as a Supper,</hi> yet the weightieſt and moſt unequal Matches commonly conclude in
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:32480:71"/>diſcord, diſcontent, and feparation, ſometimes of bodies, always of minds. If thou being mean, obtain a great For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; if ſhe have not <hi>diſcretion</hi> to know her diſtance, and eſpecially <hi>grace</hi> to know her <hi>obedience,</hi> ſhe will daily be objecting her own worthineſs, and debaſing the ſtate ſhe affirms <hi>ſingly</hi> (and nothing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſting in thy ſelf) to have rais'd thee from.
<note place="margin">Prov. 21.19.</note> 
                  <hi>It is better to dwell in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, than with a contentious and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry woman.</hi> It would be much won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, and I think there would be great cauſe, if a <hi>young, beautiful</hi> and <hi>wealthy</hi> Lady ſhould marry againſt her friends conſent, a <hi>deformed, poor,</hi> yet <hi>wiſe man.</hi> But Hiſtory informs us how <hi>Hipparchia</hi> accompliſh'd as aforeſaid, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently and for vertues ſake tied her ſelf by <hi>Matrimony</hi> to the Philoſopher <hi>Crates.</hi> Thirdly and chiefly, reſpect her qualifications. <hi>Houſes and Riches</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) are the inheritance of Fathers;
<note place="margin">Prov. 19.14.</note> but a Prudent wife is from the Lord.</hi> He that Marries only a <hi>fair face,</hi> or a <hi>full bag,</hi> ties himſelf to a <hi>foul bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Beauty</hi> in the face, and <hi>folly</hi> in the head, be two <hi>worms</hi> that fret life and waſte goods. If my <hi>Citizen</hi> eſpouſes
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:32480:71"/>a <hi>peaceable</hi> and <hi>vertuous</hi> Woman, he will attain Heaven on Earth, wealth in want, and comfort in woe. Therefore he muſt heedfully mark her inward perfections, value her for her uſeful parts, and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely expect the higheſt felicity to be compaſs'd with a <hi>Wife</hi> to lie in her <hi>head,</hi> and not in her <hi>heels:</hi> for though <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing</hi> be an ornament, <hi>Prudence</hi> is far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond it; a minde deck'd with <hi>Huſwifery,</hi> excells (principally in a <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily) all the tires of dancing, ſinging, dreſſing, and whatever an idle, ſluggiſh, licouriſh, wanton and fooliſh woman can plead for. <hi>Favour is deceitful,
<note place="margin">Pro. 31.30 31.</note> and beauty is vain; but a woman that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Lord ſhall be praiſed. Give her of the fruit of her hands, and let her own works praiſe her.
<note place="margin">Pro. 14.1.</note> Every Wiſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man buildeth her houſe; but a fooliſh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man pulleth it down.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Suppoſing now my <hi>Citizen</hi> to be Married, as reſpecting his Poſterity and the Kingdom, he muſt not let her ſpend too much, leſt his Poſterity rue it, or he be diſabled to do others good.</p>
               <p>Among many faults of <hi>She-Citizens,</hi> their <hi>pride</hi> as a <hi>Saul</hi> is <hi>higher</hi> by head and ſhoulders than the reſt. Not that it
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:32480:72"/>is greater or more common than their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſins, but more ſeen, and ſo the leſs dangerous. Many, if not ſtinted by their Huſbands, would hold it no vanity to walk in the path of <hi>Poppeia, Nero</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubine, <hi>whoſe Horſes were ſhod with Gold. Few</hi> of them have a kindneſs for <hi>Philon</hi>'s <hi>Wife,</hi> becauſe, once aſk'd why ſhe went ſo <hi>plainly apparel'd,</hi> ſhe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Her Husbands vertues were Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſufficient for her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For redreſs of this evil, let Huſbands ſhew them good Examples, by going plain themſelves; and their Wives, if they have any grace, goodneſs, love, or obedience, will be aſham'd to do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. If their own pattern fails, they muſt uſe the authority of Huſbands, and reſtrain them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let not a woman rule;</hi> it's the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles counſel;
<note place="margin">Eph. 5.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Let wives be ſubject to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Husbands. A woman</hi> (ſaith <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>) once made equal with man, beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth his Superiour.</hi> A womans rule is her huſband. My <hi>Citizens</hi> wife muſt have no power over him; for ſuffer her to day to tread upon thy foot, and to morrow ſhe will not ſtick to ſet her foot on thy neck. <hi>Semiramis</hi> the wife of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:32480:72"/>
                  <hi>Ninus</hi> King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> obtaining of him the government of the Kingdom for five days, and that his Nobles ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey her during that time; ſhe cauſed him to be preſently apprehended, and caſt into Priſon; who impatient of this diſgrace, daſh'd out his own brains. If my <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xorious Citizen,</hi> notwithſtanding what's juſt now related, will take no notice, as being acted by a <hi>Pagan,</hi> let him hearken to what St <hi>Hierom</hi> ſays: <hi>A wiſe man muſt love his wife with judgment, not blinde aſſection.</hi> Though he may not dote on her,
<note place="margin">Col. 3.19.</note> he muſt not <hi>be bitter towards her:</hi> opprobrious terms, and rough dealing, have made <hi>women</hi> caſt off their ſubmiſſive and milde nature. <hi>Clytemneſtra</hi> the wife of <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>harſhly</hi> uſed, and injuriouſly treated by him, fell into <hi>adultery,</hi> and then ſlew him. <hi>A naughty perſon,
<note place="margin">Pro. 6.12.17.20.</note> a wicked man, walketh with a froward mouth, and findeth no good. Cato</hi> a ſworn enemy to women, never ſtruck his wife. It's the part of an eſteemed huſband, to be <hi>wiſe</hi> in words, <hi>milde</hi> in converſation, and <hi>patient</hi> in importunity.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, the counſel of the Learned Emperour <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> is of mighty
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:32480:73"/>moment: If any one (ſays he) intends to live peaceably with his Wife, he ought above all things to obſerve this Rule: <hi>To admoniſh her often, to chide her ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; but never to lay hands on her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let him walk <hi>chaſtly</hi> towards her; let him be to her, as he deſires ſhe ſhould be to him. The <hi>luſt</hi> of one, being the <hi>fault;</hi> the <hi>luſt</hi> of tother may be the <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.
<note place="margin">Pro. 31.3.</note> Give not thy ſtrength to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, nor thy ways to that which deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Kings. Luſt</hi> was the cauſe of <hi>Rome</hi>'s firſt alteration in government: It brought King <hi>David</hi> to the choice of <hi>Sword</hi> or <hi>Peſtilence:</hi> It drew away <hi>Solomon</hi>'s heart from worſhipping his Creatour: It brought the <hi>Moores</hi> into <hi>Spain,</hi> whence ſince they have been ſo hardly driven; and finally, occaſioned <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> that famous <hi>Athenian,</hi> to be burnt in his Bed. Therefore hearken to <hi>Solomon,</hi> who was once involved to the hazard of his life everlaſting; but lived to recant his errour, and to <hi>queſtion</hi> and <hi>adviſe</hi> thee. <hi>Why wilt thou my Son be raviſh'd with a ſtrange woman,
<note place="margin">Pro. 5.20, 21.</note> and embrace the boſome of a ſtranger? For the ways of a man are before the eyes of the Lord, and he pondereth all his goings.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:32480:73"/>
               <p>Laſtly, if that Act of Parliament was revived, which was procured by <hi>Adam Francis</hi> Mayor, in the 25 of <hi>Edw.</hi> the third, That all <hi>known Whores</hi> ſhould be diſtinguiſh'd by their head-attires, from honeſt women, What a world of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons would forſake a Calling ſo vile and abominable, chiefly ſo remarquable and obvious to ſcoffs and curſes? And <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> would be deter'd the keeping o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly ſuch ſcandalous and pernicious Company.</p>
               <p>Let him practice <hi>lenity</hi> and not ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <hi>clemency</hi> and not tyranny; or a good womans patience may be turn'd to fury: if ſhe does not perform ſuch buſineſs as he puts her upon, with that wiſdom he expects, he muſt bear with her. He muſt ſight with <hi>fleſh, blood,</hi> and <hi>corruption,</hi> to attain <hi>Socrates</hi> humour, <hi>who was all one at home as abroad.</hi> That womans wit is reckoned pregnant enough, that can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern her Husband's bed from a Stranger's. If ſhe chance to be angry, let him uſe <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> his patience; who was the better enabled to converſe with <hi>perverſe</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons abroad, by <hi>hearing</hi> and <hi>enduring</hi> his wife <hi>Zantippe</hi> at home.</p>
               <p>Let him be willing and endeavour to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:32480:74"/>ſtruct her with <hi>Meekneſs when ſhe oppoſes her ſelf.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.25.</note> He is bound not onely to walk with his <hi>wife</hi> as a man of <hi>love,</hi> but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as a man of <hi>underſtanding.</hi> It is mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous to ſee the head ſtand where the feet ſhould be; and a double pity, when a <hi>Nabal</hi> and an <hi>Abigail</hi> are match'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But if thou haſt a <hi>Wife</hi> whoſe wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom needs not thy inſtruction, thank <hi>God; For whoſo findeth a wife,
<note place="margin">Prov. 19.22.</note> findeth a good thing, and obtaineth favour of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, let him ſhew kindneſs to her at his death. There was a Law amongſt the Ancient <hi>Romans,</hi> That no man ſhould make his <hi>Wife</hi> or onely <hi>Daughter</hi> Heir. Nothing I think can be more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt: <hi>God</hi> himſelf hath commanded, <hi>If a Man die,
<note place="margin">Num. 27.8</note> and hath no Son, then he ſhall turn his inheritance to his Daughter:</hi> and <hi>Divinity,</hi> which hath taught men to <hi>Love</hi> their Wives, hath likewiſe to <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for them.</hi> Yet diſcretion muſt allot them no more than enough. For we often ſee a mans enemies enjoy his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and the fruits of his ſweat, care and toyl. How much good might thoſe many thouſands (which ſeveral Citizens have left) have done to the <hi>Poor,</hi> to <hi>Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitals,</hi> to <hi>Schools</hi> of <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:32480:74"/>to repairing of <hi>Churches,</hi> and in other <hi>uſes,</hi> more beneficial to the <hi>Publick,</hi> more laſting to perpetuate a mans name; and I verily believe, more neceſſary to their Wives happineſs, who, if living lower, and not having the means to ſtir up in them the ambition of becoming a <hi>Lady</hi> forſooth, had avoided thoſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and misfortunes, the greedy deſire of <hi>Honour</hi> hath too frequently plunged them in. Therefore my <hi>Citizen</hi> muſt be wary and Charitable when he makes his <hi>Will,</hi> leſt his Family be ruin'd, through the folly of a Woman, too weak to bear the load of a great Eſtate, whoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement and profitable diſtribution re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires an able head, a ſolid judgment, and a minde not <hi>gariſh, vain</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſely expenſive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In 1439, and the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth, <hi>Philip Malpas</hi> Sheriff of <hi>London,</hi> at his deceaſe gave 120 l. to poor Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and every year for five years fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing 400 Shirts and Smocks, 40 pair of Sheets, and 150 Gowns of Frize to the Poor; to poor Maids marriages 100 Marks; towards mending the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways 100 Marks; beſides, to 500 poor people in <hi>London</hi> Six ſhillings and eight pence apiece.</p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:32480:75"/>
               <p>Sir <hi>William Copinger</hi> Mayor,
<note place="margin">Stows <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey.</hi>
                  </note> in the fourth of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8, at his death, gave half he was worth to his Wife, and the other half to the Poor, and other pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous uſes.</p>
               <p>Behaving himſelf thus towards his Wife, his care and kindneſs alſo muſt extend towards the reſt of his Charge, Children and Apprentices. <hi>Train up a Childe in the way he ſhould go,
<note place="margin">Pro. 22.6.</note> and when he is old he will not depart from it. Dionyſius</hi> King of <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> meaning to revenge himſelf on <hi>Dion</hi> a <hi>Syracuſean,</hi> who made war upon him, caus'd his Son to be brought up in riot and wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. This labour many Men ſave their Enemies, and do it themſelves, proving miſerable Governours of diſſolute young ones. What hope can our <hi>City</hi> have of thoſe Youth, whoſe debauchedneſs hath not been obſtructed by good Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation?</p>
               <p>The <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> reproach highly our <hi>Citizens</hi> negligence; for they were wont to chuſe <hi>Publick Tutours</hi> for the education of <hi>Citizens,</hi> bringing them up, and fitting them upon emergent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions for their Countries ſervice: but we have ſo little reſpect to the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:32480:75"/>of Vertue, that moſt of us would rather let all periſh for want of Example, than practiſe with ſome hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (an enemy to voluptuouſneſs) thoſe <hi>Exerciſes</hi> which keep the body ſound, clean, and healthful, ſtrengthen the brain, further the diſpatch of buſineſs, ſpur up others to overtake us in ſuch honourable and profitable courſes, awe all under our command from committing lewdneſs, invite to tread in our ſteps, and laſtly wipe off from us that impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation <hi>Hipperides</hi> a <hi>Grecian</hi> Philoſopher lay'd on one, who told him he had ſent his Son to travail with a ſlave for his Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; <hi>You have done notably</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>for inſtead of one Slave, at his return you ſhall receive two.</hi> I wiſh Fathers had leſs cauſe to charge <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> for their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate harſhneſs, &amp; ſleighting regards towards their Children: for moſt are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſſolutely careleſs, or unreaſonably rigid; governing either as if Servants needed no reſtraint or freedom.</p>
               <p>It's remarkable, few good <hi>Citizens</hi> Sons but degenerate from their Fathers: They know ſuch ways of <hi>ſpending</hi> their Fathers were wiſely ignorant of; but thoſe of <hi>ſaving</hi> are as diſtant from their
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:32480:76"/>inclination, as the ſearch of <hi>America</hi> was to <hi>Europeans</hi> a thouſand years ago. They like <hi>Cicero</hi>'s Son, reſemble their Fathers only in name. To redreſs ſuch deſtructive heedleſſneſs whereto <hi>Maſters</hi> are ſo prone, if they look for any bleſſing from <hi>Providence,</hi> in the name of <hi>God</hi> let them begin ſuch a kind of life as may be judg'd <hi>holy, upright,</hi> and <hi>godly.</hi> And as where there is a ſmoak, there is ſome fire; the Grace of the Almighty may by degrees work ſuch a change, that their <hi>Souls, Sons, Servants</hi> and <hi>Succeſs</hi> in their endeavours, ſhall finde an equal and laſting improvement.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs let my <hi>Citizen</hi> conſult theſe few following rules. Suffer neither Son (if capable of doing any thing) or Servant to be idle. It was great and good policy in the <hi>Romans,</hi> to let their youth learn nothing ſitting. The beſt Common-Wealths have allow'd them <hi>Theaters</hi> and <hi>ſpacious fields</hi> for their exerciſes; and the <hi>Republicans</hi> have allowed their <hi>Youth</hi> time to perform them. In the Eleventh year of <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th, to the aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of beholders, for Eight days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in the preſence of his then Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, accompanied by the moſt of the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:32480:76"/>Nobles and great Eſtates of the Realm, near <hi>Clerken-Well</hi> was ſhewn all the skill and cunning that Age and the renowned activity of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> could put forth, in ſuch Exerciſes, of <hi>hands</hi> or <hi>feet,</hi> as far excelling ſmoaking and drinking, as ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>Great</hi> Horſe does a Hobby: For the firſt being manly and healthful, the laſt is effeminate, ridiculous, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the body. Finally, upon more than bare Quarterly days, if ſome of the moſt Eminent and reputed <hi>Citizens</hi> uſed to be preſent in places of Publick Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, there to praiſe, to encourage, and ſometimes to reward Young men that were active; what an alteration would there be in the cuſtoms of a World! How would young men abſtain exceſſes and riotting, to preſerve their ſtrengths? how would they by their Service oblige their Maſters to diſpenſe with a ſpace of time, now and then, for them to ſhew themſelves active, skilful, and emulous of glory? which though it be vain in the practice of Vertue, yet it's always ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with the hope of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding themſelves more knowingly in proceſs of time. <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> by Nature viciouſly enclin'd, was ſo inflam'd with
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:32480:77"/>the fame of <hi>Miltiades,</hi> fung by all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſo ardently emulated his deeds, that from a deprav'd and looſe perſon he became a virtuous and renowned Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
               <p>In the next place my <hi>Citizen</hi> muſt look bountifully on the <hi>Poor.</hi> I ſhould have ſpoken a little of <hi>Hoſpitality</hi> in a place foregoing, amongſt my <hi>Citizens</hi> needleſs expences. But Vice having almoſt rooted out a <hi>Vertue</hi> ſo many ſhar'd in formerly in our Land, and of late years it lying even breathleſs; I ſhall touch on it lightly in my treating of <hi>Charity,</hi> to make the memory of our Heathen An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors appear more amiable and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary, and to quicken my <hi>Citizen</hi> for the amplification of that we call <hi>good Houſe-keeping.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charity</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine) is the way of man to God, and of God to man.</hi> Is my <hi>Citizen</hi> great and wealthy, and would have his Riches known? let him do it then by gifts. <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Roman</hi> grandeur, that is was leſs diſcern'd by what it took, than by what it gave. If occaſions for doing good be not offred, ſeek them. Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful works are accepted of God as Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:32480:77"/>yea better than Sacrifice. <hi>Anthony</hi> Prince of <hi>Salern,</hi> being ask'd what he would leave himſelf, anſwered, <hi>That which I have given.</hi> But avaricious men think all loſt that's given. When they beg in <hi>Italy,</hi> they uſe this Phraſe, <hi>Do good for your ſelves. There is that ſcattereth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) and yet encreaſeth;
<note place="margin">Prov. 11.27.</note> and there is that witholdeth more then is meet, but it tendeth to Poverty.
<note place="margin">Prov. 19.17.</note> He that hath pitty on the Poor lendeth to the Lord, and that which he hath given will he pay again.</hi> So he that forbids thee to be a Uſurer, commands thee to be ſo. <hi>Titus Veſpaſian</hi> his Son (who deſtroy'd <hi>Jeruſalem)</hi> ſo loved liberality, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring one evening he had given nothing the ſame day, he burſt out, <hi>O my friends, we have loſt this day!</hi> What a reproach is it to Chriſtians to be thus outdone by Infidels? They may be judged very well to riſe in judgment againſt us, though they were obſcurely lighted by Nature: for we generally walk as men with dark Lanthorns; they <hi>light</hi> none but themſelves, as we <hi>love</hi> none ſave our ſelves. But mark,
<note place="margin">Prov. 21.13.</note> 
                  <hi>He that ſtoppeth his ear at the cry of the Poor, he alſo ſhall cry himſelf, and not be heard.</hi> The <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:32480:78"/>made a certain Law, that no man ſhould make a publick Feaſt, except he had provided before for the Poor. Far alas! is the ſenſe of ſuch a thing from us, much leſs the imitation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cymon</hi> of <hi>Athens</hi> (ſaith a famous Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) gave a yearly penſion to the poor, fed the hungry, and cloath'd the naked. The houſe of <hi>Lucius Lucullus,</hi> was the <hi>Hoſpital</hi> of all that travail'd from <hi>Greece</hi> to <hi>Rome. Pertinax</hi> the Succeſſor of <hi>Comodus</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor, was libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral above all before or after him; he uſed to ſay, that <hi>His Lands were not proper to him alone, but common to all the people of</hi> Rome. If I would ſwell my Piece with ſuch obſervations, how bulky might it be made? but I deem what's already quoted, enough to ſhame my <hi>Citizen</hi> (if he be too cloſe-fiſted;) and to enkindle the ſparks of his charity, till his <hi>Zeal for God's Service</hi> (like <hi>David</hi>'s) <hi>conſumes him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.139.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall end this Subject by enlivening him with two or three recompens'd (as the Scripture aſſures us) and that meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for their tenderneſs and hoſpitality. <hi>Rahab</hi> on this ſcore was with all her kindred ſaved from death, when all the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:32480:78"/>people of <hi>Jericho</hi> beſides, both great and ſmall paſt the edg of the Sword. I ſhould have mention'd, formoſt,
<note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> how <hi>Lot</hi> was drawn out of <hi>Sodom</hi> by force, and preſerved from burning in it, becauſe he entertain'd moſt kindly two <hi>Angels</hi> in the ſhapes of men.
<note place="margin">2 Kings. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Eliſha</hi> to requite the charitableneſs of the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> who had conſtrained him ſo often to eat bread, reſtored her dead Son to life. And now if my <hi>Citizen</hi> can lock up his <hi>Yellow</hi> and <hi>White,</hi> rather than impart to the wants of diſtreſſed and unfortunate people, he may cloath him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in fine Linen, and fare delicately; but the doom of <hi>Dives</hi> too aſſuredly and dreadfully will at length light on him: He that denyed a Crum of bread to <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> was denyed a drop of water, when he was all afire. Alas, what is the Ocean, to the infinite World of fire in Hell? Yet <hi>Dives,</hi> unhappy and much to be pityed <hi>Dives,</hi> who waſted in his life ſo many Tuns of Wine, cannot now procure a drop of Water to cool the tip of his tongue.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, my <hi>Citizen</hi> muſt not be back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to promote the <hi>weal</hi> of the <hi>Publick,</hi> leſt at one time or other he be chaſtiſed
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:32480:79"/>by another <hi>Epaminondas,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding a miſerable <hi>Citizen</hi> of <hi>Thebes</hi> to give another a round Sum of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, was askt by him upon what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count? <hi>Becauſe</hi> (reply'd he ſharply) <hi>thou haſt robbed the Common-Wealth.</hi> An <hi>Ant</hi> is a wiſe Creature for it ſelf, but a ſhrew'd thing in an Orchard or Garden; and certainly men, that are great Lovers of themſelves, waſte the <hi>Publick. Men</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cicero) are not born for themſelves, but for their Gountrey, Parents, Kindred, and Friends.</hi> I can't hold now from reproving (with reaſon) the <hi>Cowardiſe,</hi> and <hi>fearful amazement</hi> of our late <hi>Citizens,</hi> when they ſhould have ſuccour'd ſingly or in groſs the <hi>beſt of Princes.</hi> How can the Ghoſt of <hi>Wat Tyler</hi>'s Conqueror do leſs than haunt ſuch a degenerate brood, whoſe aim is at <hi>a dignity,</hi> ſpringing from <hi>Majeſty</hi> and <hi>King-ſhip,</hi> and yet none ſtir'd before the dreadful ſtroak, <hi>with a ſingle blow,</hi> to deliver their oppreſs'd <hi>Countrey;</hi> but eſpecially a <hi>Prince</hi> that as <hi>meer man,</hi> never had his fellow upon Earth. <hi>Mutius Scaevola,</hi> that magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Roman,</hi> was poſſeſs'd with that courage, that to free the City by <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenna</hi>'s
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:32480:79"/>death, he entred the Camp alone, and killing the King's Secretary inſtead of himſelf, not knowing well to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them; notwithſtanding, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntedly juſtified his intention, by burning his hand in a fire, before <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenna</hi>'s face, ſeeming to feel no more heat, than if he warm'd it in the Sun; and thereby frighting the King to a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſing of him honourably, (though with the loſs of his right hand) and to the raiſing his Siege from before <hi>Rome. Dion</hi> of <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> never reſted till he had dethron'd <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant. <hi>Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lauros</hi> an <hi>Athenian,</hi> hearing the <hi>Oracle</hi> had pronounced the ruine of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, unleſs ſome one dyed voluntarily to expiate their crimes, caſt himſelf fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly from the walls of the City. But <hi>faint-heartedneſs, avarice, ſloath,</hi> and <hi>luxury,</hi> cauſed the fall of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> into the <hi>Great Turk's</hi> hands, <hi>Mahomet</hi> the firſt and cruel Emperour; cauſed <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> a pious vertuous Prince, and the laſt <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Emperour, to expire amidſt the horrour and confuſion of the <hi>City,</hi> and afterwards to have his Head exalted on a pole, and carried by the <hi>Turks</hi> in deriſion through the <hi>City.</hi>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:32480:80"/>The <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>ill affections,</hi> the <hi>cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize</hi> and <hi>covetouſneſs</hi> of our <hi>City,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly concur'd moſt to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable end of our <hi>Learned, Wiſe, Virtuous, Valiant, Merciful</hi> and <hi>Religious Soveraign.</hi> But as <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was deſtroyed with Fire and Sword, and deſolated, as a deſerved puniſhment on thoſe that had wherewithal, and might with eaſe have prevented their own miſeries, and their Princes: So with a kind of Authority (for I could cite a credible Prophecy for it) may I ſpeak <hi>London</hi> comparatively to have labour'd under the effects of impartial <hi>Juſtice,</hi> for their defaults and bewailable negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, in permitting <hi>Gods Anointed</hi> to be ſo ignominiouſly uſed, as was our <hi>Royal Martyr.</hi> But <hi>(Ah the Mercies of a patient and ever-loving God!)</hi> it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with this difference, as if we had been put to <hi>David</hi>'s choice, and choſe like him. Whereas <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was almoſt razed, and its Inhabitants e'n extirpated the Earth, by the rage and cruelty of <hi>Men;</hi> Our <hi>London</hi> (bleſſed be the lot) was almoſt depopulated by a <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> and its Buildings e'n con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd through <hi>Fire;</hi> but by the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:32480:80"/>and powerful hand of a moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful and reſtoring <hi>God.</hi> I may well ſay reſtoring: For what man ever read or heard of ſuch a prodigious and ſudden Rebuilding a <hi>City</hi> ſo vaſt and ruinated? who can't but admire the populouſneſs of a place, whoſe Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants had been firſt innumerably ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd by a <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> and afterwards diſpers'd into all parts of <hi>England</hi> by an entire overthrow of their dwellings? Certainly my <hi>Citizen</hi> muſt needs be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd to conſider thoſe wonders he may behold in our <hi>Phoenix-City.</hi> And it's impoſſible to refrain crying out with <hi>David,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 126.3</note> The Lord hath done great things for us, whereof we are glad.</hi> Finally, if my <hi>Citizen</hi> would be reckoned a <hi>juſt, peaceable,</hi> and <hi>profitable</hi> man; he muſt reverence the higher Powers, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by <hi>Time, Right Reaſon,</hi> and the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land. The preſent <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is moſt agreeable and conſiſtent with the <hi>Divine,</hi> moſt ſuitable to the Genius of the <hi>Nation,</hi> and the advantage of particular perſons: It is free from diſcords, emulation, and ambitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires; concluding, that, <hi>For the ſins of our Land, many were the Princes thereof.</hi>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:32480:81"/>Wherefore my <hi>Citizen,
<note place="margin">Prov. 24.21.</note> Fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with thoſe that are given to Change.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Never did <hi>London</hi> need more the aſſiſtance of Wealthy and Liberal men: for albeit, to admiration, the <hi>City</hi> ſeems almoſt Rebuilt, nevertheleſs but a ſlow hand forwards the works of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Publick good.</hi> Now is the time for my <hi>Citizen</hi> to ſhew his large and bountiful thoughts, in the acts of open <hi>Charity,</hi> and neceſſary expence. No pretences for the contrary can favour his too ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent <hi>Covetouſneſs:</hi> All his veiled excuſes are tranſparent enough, to ſee into his miſerable, fooliſh, and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy temper. How do the <hi>charitable deeds</hi> of his Predeceſſors reproach his <hi>Avarice!</hi> What a ſhame it is for a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant,</hi> whoſe reaſon is ſatisfied in what he believes, to be exceeded by meer <hi>Ignorants,</hi> who ſcarce knew any truth in the ends they propoſed themſelves, when they built <hi>Churches,</hi> erected <hi>Halls, Conduits,</hi> and other places of <hi>Common Advantage;</hi> built and endowed <hi>Colledges, Free-Schools, Hoſpitals,</hi> and <hi>Alms-houſes;</hi> when they repaired <hi>Bridges, High-ways,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ined through their <hi>Virtues,</hi> bright
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:32480:81"/>and clear, as light in a dark place. Wherefore my <hi>Citizen</hi> ought to conſider the works of ſuch as have been great <hi>Benefactors,</hi> and <hi>exemplary Promoters</hi> of the <hi>Publick good.</hi> And the better to ſtir him up, I have adjoyned hereto the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and meritorious deeds of ſome paſt <hi>Citizens;</hi> ſo that if he cuts by their Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, I have my wiſh.</p>
               <p>In the Reign of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, the ſame Sir <hi>William Walworth,</hi> (that had ſo couragiouſly kill'd <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> the Rebel,) repaired St. <hi>Michael</hi>'s Church in <hi>Crooked-Lane,</hi> and founded there a Colledge.</p>
               <p>About the year 1385. <hi>John Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Sheriff in the Ninth of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, built the <hi>Cuſtom-Houſe</hi> nigh the <hi>Tower;</hi> and was beſides a great Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of any thing was commodious for the City.</p>
               <p>In 1431. <hi>John Wells</hi> Grocer, and Mayor, he was a great Benefactour to the New building of the Chappel by <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> and erected the Standard in <hi>Weſt-Cheap</hi> at his own coſt and charges.</p>
               <p>In 1445. <hi>Simon Eyre</hi> Draper, being Mayor, built <hi>Leaden-hall,</hi> to be a common Garner for the City.</p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:32480:82"/>
               <p>In 1480. <hi>Bartholomew James,</hi> Draper and Mayor, built new the great Conduit in <hi>Weſt-Cheap.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In 1508. <hi>Ralph Jennings</hi> Merchant-Taylor being Mayor, he built the greateſt part of St. <hi>Andrews</hi> Church, called <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhaft.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In 1513. <hi>John Tare</hi> Mercer, being Mayor, he new built the Church of St. <hi>Anthonies</hi> Hoſpital in <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In 1521. Sir <hi>John Milborn</hi> Draper, being Mayor, he founded fourteen Alms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes by <hi>Croſſed-Fryers</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>In 1560. Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Cheſter</hi> being Mayor, the Merchant-Taylors founded their Free-School.</p>
               <p>My <hi>Citizen</hi> conſiderately and ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally dividing his time, between Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and Publick Intereſt, Self-love and Society, muſt uſe all honeſt and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable means in advancing the common good.</p>
               <p>In the year 1337. <hi>Walter Neal</hi> Sheriff, gave Lands towards the repair of the High-ways about <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In 1378. <hi>John Philpot</hi> a Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> ſent Ships to Sea, and ſcowred it of Pirates, taking many of them Priſoners.</p>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:32480:82"/>
               <p>In 1390. <hi>Adam Bamme</hi> Goldſmith, and Mayor, in a time of ſcarcity, ſo prudently and plentifully provided the City with Corn from beyond Sea, as the Countrey it ſelf was ſerved out of the Store.</p>
               <p>In 1486. In the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, <hi>William Horn</hi> Salter, being Mayor, and Knighted in the Field by the King; he gave to the repairing the Road between <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and ſome other wants, 500 Marks; a Sum in thoſe days of great value, and equal to above 20 times as much now.</p>
               <p>Two eſpecial ways more I ſhall inſiſt upon. Firſt, his Study ought to be Unity. <hi>Scilurus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi>) a King of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi> having many Sons, and feeling his hour to approach, called them all before him, and bid them one after another to break a bundle of <hi>Darts,</hi> laid before them to the ſame purpoſe; which being bound together, the ſtrongeſt was not able to perform; but he taking them aſunder (though very feeble) eaſily broak them: <hi>Thus ſhall it be with you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if you agree together, no man ſhall hurt you; but divided you cannot proſper:</hi> So it fares with a <hi>City;</hi> their ſafety depends
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:32480:83"/>chiefly on Unity, and a mutual conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Inferiours with Superiours. <hi>A threefold Cord is hot eaſily broken.
<note place="margin">Eccl. 4.12.</note> The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtocles</hi> the brave, and <hi>Ariſtides</hi> the juſt <hi>Athenian,</hi> were at ſuch variance, as the former told the people one day in a full Aſſembly, that unleſs both <hi>he</hi> and <hi>Ariſtides</hi> were thruſt forth of the <hi>City,</hi> it would not ſtand.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Diſcord</hi> then between two men of their wiſdom was ſo dangerous, how dreadful would it appear, hatcht under Faction and Ignorance? Briefly, Concord maketh ſmall things mightily to encreaſe; but Diviſion decays and deſtroyeth the wealth, peace, ſtrength and Unity of Families, Cities, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms themſelves.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I could wiſh <hi>Citizens</hi> did not ſo much increaſe the number of <hi>Apprentices,</hi> as in theſe times they do. It's ſtrange inferiour Trades ſhould in their policy this way exceed thoſe of a higher rank. It's probable ſcarce one Artificer in five, could have been em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd three days in a Week, without the laudable courſe of reſtraining a man to one or two <hi>Apprentices</hi> in his appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time; which hath wrought this
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:32480:83"/>effect, that none in theſe <hi>Callings</hi> ſo ordered, can (unleſs the fault be his own) complain for want of work.</p>
               <p>In taking many <hi>Apprentices,</hi> a man's <hi>Secrets</hi> are open to more than one, and the likelier to be diſcovered, to his own diſadvantage, but eſpecially to the <hi>hurt</hi> of the Publick.</p>
               <p>A man that hath had a good ſtock to begin with, being brought to decay, is it not a thouſand pities, that having paid a Sum of Money at his entrance, and diſcharged all requiſite Duties in the <hi>City,</hi> he ſhall be forc'd to beg or ſtarve in it, or go out of it for a Living?</p>
               <p>Again, many a <hi>Young man</hi> which ſhall not have, or for the preſent hath not a ſufficient ſtock of Money or Credit to begin; is it not pity he ſhould leave the City? In the year 1371. <hi>John Barns</hi> Mercer, and Mayor, gave a Cheſt with three Locks, and one thouſand Marks to be Lent to poor young men. Yet while men may have what number of <hi>Apprentices</hi> they pleaſe, it ſhall be very hard for either of theſe to finde em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. To redreſs this, fewer <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices</hi> ought to be taken, and thoſe for a longer time than ordinary. 'Tis
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:32480:84"/>not fit, that every <hi>child,</hi> becauſe a good Sum of Money is given with him, ſhould be bound but for ſeven years; which expired, he iſſues out a <hi>Maſter,</hi> before he be a <hi>Man.</hi> Thus the ſplendour of the <hi>City</hi> grows dimmer and dimmer, and <hi>Boys</hi> ſtand in Shop-Doors, in the places of perſonable men; which is an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, ſomething akin to that, <hi>Woe to thee O Land,
<note place="margin">Ec. 10.16.</note> when thy King is a Child.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things conſidered, let the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good</hi> of all be rather endeavoured, than the <hi>particular</hi> of a few: Every <hi>private</hi> man is a Servant to the <hi>Publick;</hi> it is very diſproportionable, for Servants to be preferred before their Maſters; for <hi>when a Servant reigns,
<note place="margin">Prov. 30.31.</note> the earth is diſquieted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have I led my <hi>Citizen</hi> through the Labyrinth of a <hi>Trading</hi> life, to his Temporal and Eternal profit; if he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temns not in my directions the Counſel of <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt man ever was, or will be; the judgments and acts of the moſt lov'd, admir'd, and worthily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned men <hi>Antiquity</hi> can boaſt of; and finally, the real, durable, nay ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:32480:84"/>benefits and poſſeſſions, which a <hi>juſt diligence</hi> will procure him here, and a <hi>righteous uſe</hi> beſtow on him here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; beſides the honour, praiſe, and reverence his very name and memory will exact from poſterity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A man ſhall not be eſtabliſhed by wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs,
<note place="margin">Prov. 12.3.</note> but the root of the Righteous ſhall not be moved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A good name is better than precious Ointment,
<note place="margin">Ecc. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and the day of Death is better than the day of ones Birth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The juſt man walketh in his integrity,
<note place="margin">Prov. 20.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> his Children are bleſſed after him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
